<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The Jesuites policy to suppress monarchy proving out of their own writings that the Protestant religion is a sure foundation and principle of a true Christian / written by a person of honor.</title>
            <author>Derby, Charles Stanley, Earl of, 1628-1672.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1678</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 124 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 19 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">B21181</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing D1088</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">18459597</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 18459597</idno>
            <idno type="VID">206445</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. B21181)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 206445)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1631:14)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The Jesuites policy to suppress monarchy proving out of their own writings that the Protestant religion is a sure foundation and principle of a true Christian / written by a person of honor.</title>
                  <author>Derby, Charles Stanley, Earl of, 1628-1672.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[8], 27 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for William Cademan ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1678.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Caption title on p. [1]: A dialogue between Orthodox, a royalist, and Cacodæmon, one popishly affected.</note>
                  <note>Attributed to Derby by Wing and NUC pre-1956 imprints.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Huntington Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Jesuits --  England.</term>
               <term>Jesuits --  Controversial literature.</term>
               <term>Protestantism --  Apologetic works.</term>
               <term>Royalists --  England.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-08</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-08</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-11</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-11</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:206445:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE JESUITES POLICY TO Suppreſs Monarchy, Proving out of their own WRITINGS THAT THE Proteſtant Religion IS A SURE FOUNDATION AND PRINCIPLE OF A True Chriſtian.</p>
            <p>Written by a Perſon of Honor.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>William Cademan,</hi> at the <hi>Pope</hi>'s <hi>Head</hi> in the Lower Walls of the <hi>New-Exchange,</hi> 1678.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:206445:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:206445:2"/>
            <head>To all Supreme Powers, by what Titles ſoever Dignified, or Diſtin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſhed, <hi>i. e.</hi> To <hi>Emperors, Kings, Sovereign Princes, Re-publicks,</hi> &amp;c.</head>
            <p>TO You (Gods Vice-gerents on Earth, over all Perſons, whether Eccleſiaſtical or Temporal, next under god within Your own reſpective Dominions Supreme Governors,) I conceive fitteſt to Dedicate, and Direct the enſuing Papers; to You (Moſt Illuſtrious,) they addreſs themſelves, as to perſons moſt concern'd in the Subject they treat about; whereby is endeavored the Vindication of Gods Honor, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in as his Vice-gerents You are highly concern'd; alſo Your own Supreme Powers and Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thorities, which in former Ages, (and yet ſtill in the Doctrinal part,) have been of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten Invaded by the Biſhop of <hi>Rome,</hi> and their Abettors; amongſt whom the <hi>Jeſuites</hi> have been ſtill in the Front, as the principal Champions againſt You; and for thoſe Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops from whom all Anti-Monarchical Principles have proceeded under the veil and cover of other Religions, —as <hi>Quakers, Anabaptiſts, Independents,</hi> &amp;c. which ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral Sects have been Abetted by ſeveral of the <hi>Roman</hi> Clergy, (thereunto Authorized and commanded by the Biſhops of <hi>Rome,</hi>) to prevent a Reformation amongſt themſelves (always a terror to them,) and the better to d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>vide the Reformed Churches over the World, according to that Maxim, <hi>Divide &amp; Impera,</hi> —whereby they have not a little impeded the Chriſtian Profeſſion, in the Inlargement of the Kingdom of Chriſt, and thereby given occaſion to the Enemies of God (the <hi>Turks,</hi> &amp;c.) to Blaſpheme, and enlarge their Dominions and Territories; hereby the Iſle of <hi>Rhodes</hi> and <hi>Candie</hi> has been loſt, to the Eternal reproach of the Chriſtian Profeſſion; for while Chriſtians are disjoyned, the common Enemy takes the advantage, which by a happy <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nion, ho would loſe.</p>
            <p>I ſhall here add a few particulars out of the Hiſtory of <hi>France,</hi> in the Life of <hi>Lewis</hi> the Thirteenth; <hi>Fol. 1295.</hi> 
               <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>pon occaſion of the Murther of <hi>Henry</hi> the Fourth of <hi>France</hi> by <hi>Ravilliac;</hi> the words be theſe. —This wicked Murtherer confeſſed no other motive of his crime, but the Book of <hi>Mariana,</hi> a <hi>Spaniſh Jeſuite;</hi> which Book by a decree made by the Colledge of <hi>Sorbonne,</hi> and confirmed by a Sentence from the Courts of Parliament, was for that cauſe condemned to be publickly burnt before our <hi>Lady</hi> Church in <hi>Paris:</hi> the tenor of the Sentence was;</p>
            <p>
               <hi>[The Court, the great Chamber the Turnelle, and the Chamber of the Edict being Aſſembled, having ſeen the decree of the faculty of Divinity aſſembled the Fourth of this Month of</hi> June, <hi>according to a Sentence given in</hi> May <hi>laſt, upon the renewing of the cenſure in matter of Doctrine made by the ſaid faculty in the Year 1413. Confirmed by the Holy Council of</hi> Conſtance; <hi>that it is an He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſie full of Impiety to maintain that it is lawful for Subjects or Strangers, upon any pretence or cauſe whatſoever, to attempt againſt the Sacred Perſon of Kings and Sovereign Princes, the Book of</hi> John Mariana <hi>Intitled,</hi> De Rege, &amp; Regis In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitutione, <hi>Printed as well at Mentz as in other places, containing many execra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Blaſphemies againſt the Deceaſed King</hi> Henry <hi>the Third of moſt happy Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mory, the perſons and Eſtates of Kings and Sovereign Princes, and other propo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitions contrary to the ſaid decree: upon the concluſion of the Kings Atturney General, the matter being propounded; the ſaid Court hath and doth ordain, that the ſaid decree of the Fourth of this preſent month of <hi>June</hi> ſhall be entered
<pb facs="tcp:206445:3"/>into the Regiſters thereof, and heard at the inſtance of the Kings Atturny Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral, and read every year on the like day, on Sunday, in the Pariſhes of this City, and Suburbs of</hi> Paris; <hi>it doth alſo ordain that the Book of</hi> Mariana <hi>ſhall be burnt by the Executioner of Juſtice, before our</hi> Lady <hi>Church in</hi> Paris; <hi>for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bidding all men, of what Eſtates, Quality and Condition ſoever they be, upon pain of High Treaſon, to write or cauſe any Books to be Printed againſt the ſaid Decree and Sentence; it doth alſo enjoyn, that Copies taken out of the Origi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nals of the ſaid Decree, and this preſent Sentence, ſhall be ſent unto the</hi> Baile<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wicks <hi>and</hi> Seneſhauſhes <hi>of this Juriſdiction, there to be read and publiſhed after the accuſtomed manner and form. And moreover, at Evenſong in Pariſhes, in Towns, Suburbs, and other Burroughs, the firſt Sunday of</hi> June; <hi>enjoyning all</hi> Bayliffs <hi>and</hi> Seneſhalls <hi>to proceed to the ſaid publication, and the ſubſtitutes of the Kings Atturny General to have a care of the Execution, and to certifie the Court of their Diligence.]</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>pon A Declaration, or Letter from one <hi>Cotton</hi> the <hi>Jeſuite</hi> to the <hi>Queen Regent,</hi> to wipe off that Aſperſion from their Society, An Anſwr is framed unto it, by the name of <hi>Anti-Cotton,</hi> which you will find in <hi>Fol. 1298.</hi> The words be as follow.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Anti-Cotton,</hi> the Doctrine of <hi>Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuites</hi> for Mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thering Kings.</note>[Francis Ribadinera <hi>writing of the parricide of</hi> James Clement, <hi>he ſaith, foraſmuch as the reſolution</hi> Henry <hi>the Third took upon him, was the advice of a Polititian, and a</hi> Machiaviliſt, <hi>not con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formable to the rules of our Saviour, behold the reaſon, that by the judgment of God, the ſaid</hi> Henry <hi>was kill'd by a young Monk, and dyed by the ſtroke of a Knife.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Carolus Scribanius,</hi> a <hi>Flemiſh Jeſuite,</hi> who calls himſelf <hi>Clarus Bonarſcius,</hi> in his Book Entituled <hi>Amphitheatrum honoris,</hi> ſayes, that if it ſo fall out, that a <hi>Denis,</hi> a <hi>Machonidas,</hi> or an <hi>Ariſtotimus,</hi> Monſters of their Age, oppreſs <hi>France,</hi> ſhall not the <hi>Pope</hi> have abſolute power to animate againſt them ſome <hi>Dion, Timoleon,</hi> or <hi>Phil<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poemen,</hi> that is to ſay, tamers and ſuppreſſers of Monſters? And afterwards ſpeaking of a Tyrant waſting <hi>France,</hi> will no man (ſayes he) take Armes againſt that Tyrant waſting <hi>France?</hi> Will no <hi>Pope</hi> ſet free that Noble Kingdom from the ſtroke of the Axe?</p>
            <p>He cites <hi>Bellarmine,</hi> who although he condemneth Treaſon againſt Princes, yet in ambiguous terms he ſeems to approve it, by commending <hi>Garnet</hi> the <hi>Jeſuite,</hi> in theſe words. <hi>Wherefore was</hi> Henry Garnet, <hi>a man unmatchable in all kinds of Learn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and Holineſs of Life, ſo puniſhed in the higheſt Degree, but only for that he would not detect that, which with a ſafe conſcience he could not?</hi> And the ſame Author, in his Book <hi>De Pontifice Romano,</hi> ſayes, the <hi>Pope</hi> may diſpoſe of Kingdoms, taking from one, and giving to another, as being the Superior Prince Eccleſiaſtical; and the <hi>Jeſuite Gretzer</hi> ſayes, we are not ſuch Daſtards, as that we fear to affirm openly, that the <hi>Pope</hi> of <hi>Rome</hi> may (if neceſſity ſo require) free his Catholick Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects from their Oath of Obedience, if their Sovereign intreat them Tyrannically; yea he adds, in the ſame place; that if the <hi>Pope</hi> do it diſcreetly and warily, it is a meri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torious work; after all this, he quotes the Doctrine of <hi>Tolet, Mariana,</hi> and <hi>John Guignard,</hi> a <hi>Jeſuite</hi> Prieſt reſiding in <hi>Paris,</hi> who had written a Treatiſe in praiſe of <hi>James Clement,</hi> with divers motives to make away the King which laſt dyed; for the which he was Executed. But <hi>Francis Verona Conſtant,</hi> exceeds them all; he affirms,
<pb facs="tcp:206445:3"/>that notwithſtanding the <hi>Council</hi> of <hi>Conſtance,</hi> it is lawful for any private man to Murther Kings condemned of Hereſie and Tyranny: And <hi>Emanuel Sa</hi> writes, that that the Rebellion of a Clerk againſt the King is no Treaſon, inſomuch that he is not Subject to him; the which <hi>Bellarmine</hi> in a manner confirms; ſaying, the <hi>Pope</hi> of <hi>Rome</hi> hath Exempted Clerks from their ſubjection to Princes: Kings are now no more Supe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riors of Clerks. And to prove their Doctrine of killing Kings more plainly, he produ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceth the equivocations and evaſions of <hi>Garnet,</hi> being apprehended for the Powder-Treaſon; the which is juſtified by many of that Society: <hi>John Henreux</hi> writing thus: <hi>When any man is drawn into queſtion under an unjuſt trial, no man ſtanding bound to inform againſt himſelf (as the law of nature teacheth us plainly) he may peremp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torily, and freely deny that for which he is called into queſtion, without any tergiverſation, becauſe he always underſtands this Clauſe, [Ut tenear dicere]</hi> which Doctrine is confirmed by divers other <hi>Jeſuites;</hi> One of them affirming, that the Doctrine of Equivocation is grounded upon the memorable Example of St. <hi>Francis:</hi> in the end he ſhows their opinion touching concealing of Confeſſion, which they hold ought not to be revealed. <hi>John Henreux,</hi> writing of that Subject, ſayes: <hi>That a thing Sealed up with the moſt holy Signet of Confeſſion, cannot be broken without deteſtable Sacriledge: and that there cannot fall ſo great a miſchief, for the avoid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of which it can be lawful to bewray a Confeſſion.</hi> And <hi>Suarez</hi> adds; yea though the ſafety of the whole Common-weale ſhould ſtand upon it; by all which proof<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> he ſhews, that it was not <hi>Mariana</hi>'s Doctrine alone to Murther Kings, but that all the <hi>Jeſuites</hi> have erred with him in this; whom <hi>Father Cotton</hi> connot juſtifie, in ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral. <hi>Anti-Cotton</hi> having ſet down the <hi>Jeſuites</hi> Doctrine, he proves it by their Actions, and firſt, by the Fact of <hi>John Chaſtel,</hi> Clerk,<note place="margin">Confirmed by the Actions.</note> brought up in the <hi>Jeſuites</hi> Colledge; who having Stabbed the King in the Mouth, the <hi>27.</hi> of <hi>December, 1604.</hi> being examined upon ſundry Queſtions, and among others, wh ther he had ſtudied Divinity in the <hi>Jeſuites</hi> Colledge; he anſwered, that he had been th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>re und<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>r Fath<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>r <hi>Gueet,</hi> with whom he had continued two years and a half: And being ask<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>d if he had ever been in the Chamber of Meditation, (whither the <hi>Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuites</hi> uſe to bring the greateſt Sinners, there to behold the Repreſentation of many De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vils, ſet forth (under colour to reduce them to a better Life) thereby to cauſe a per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turbation in their minds, and conſequently, upon ſuch reſolutions, to thruſt them forward to the undertaking of ſome gr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>at Action) His anſwer was, that he had often been in the Chamber of Meditations: And being queſtioned, whether the killing of the King were not an ordinary diſc urſe amongſt the <hi>Jeſuites,</hi> anſwered, that he had heard them ſay, <hi>it was lawful to kill the King, and that he was no member of the Church, and that we ought not to obey him, nor hold him for our King, untill he had receiv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed approbation from the Pope.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Peter Barriere</hi> being apprehended at <hi>Melun,</hi> in <hi>April, 1593.</hi> being d ſcovered by an honeſt Fryer, Confeſſed, that he came purpoſely to Court, to kill the King; and that he had been p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>rſwaded thereunto by one <hi>Varade,</hi> a <hi>Jeſuite,</hi> whoſe dayly practice was to d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>fame the King with v<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>le Speeches, by wh ſe perſwaſion he had provided a Knife to do the Fact: he firſt of all diſcovered his intent to <hi>Aubrey,</hi> Curate of St. <hi>Andrew des Acts,</hi> who directed him to <hi>Varade,</hi> Rector of the <hi>Jeſuites</hi> Coll<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>dge, who confirmed him in his Reſolution to kill the King; aſſuring h m that in caſe he were put to death, he ſhould obtain in Heaven a Crown of Martyrdom; and adjuring him unto this Action,
<pb facs="tcp:206445:4"/>upon the Sacrament of Confeſſion, and to Holy Communion. And (omitting many Actions of <hi>Jeſuites,</hi> both at home, and abroad, to prove their damnable Doctrine) he concludes with <hi>Garnet, Hall,</hi> and others of the Sect, who were Complices in that Pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>r-Treaſon which was practiſed to ruine the King, and the whole Eſtates of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In the end, he ſeeks to prove by many pregnant preſumptions, that the <hi>Jeſuites</hi> are guilty of the Murther. Firſt, by an Advertiſement ſent from <hi>M. de la force,</hi> the Kings Lievtenant in <hi>Bearn,</hi> that a <hi>Spaniard,</hi> deſcribed by him was come into <hi>France</hi> with an intent to kill the King; which <hi>Spaniard</hi> was brought unto the King by <hi>Cotton;</hi> but the King having received theſe Letters, ſhewed them to <hi>Cotton,</hi> and commanded him to bring the <hi>Spaniard</hi> again, but he could not be found.</p>
            <p n="2">
               <hi>2.</hi> Secondly, the ſeditious Preaching of <hi>Gontier,</hi> and <hi>Hardy,</hi> both <hi>Jeſuites,</hi> the Lent before the Fact was committed; inſomuch that the Marſhal <hi>D'Ornano</hi> told the King, that if <hi>Gontier</hi> had Preached ſo at <hi>Bourdeaux,</hi> he would have cauſed him to be caſt into the River; and yet he was as very <hi>Zealous Catholick.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">
               <hi>3.</hi> Thirdly, the Confeſſion of <hi>Ravilliac,</hi> who juſtified unto <hi>Father Aubigny,</hi> that he had told him in Confeſſion, that he had been ſent to give a great blow, and that he had ſhewed him the Knife, having a heart graven upon it; But the <hi>Jeſuit</hi> proteſted, <q>That God had given him the grace to forget that preſently which was revealed to him in Confeſſion; <hi>whereby he ſaved his Life.</hi>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>And laſt of all, the Predictions before the Kings death as at <hi>Bruxelles,</hi> it was ſpoken of twelve, or fifteen days before it happened. At <hi>Prague,</hi> it had been given out, that the King was dead, before it fell out ſo; and moreover, it was told them, that after his death the <hi>Daulphin</hi> ſhould not be King, but the King of <hi>Spain;</hi> and that for ſome reaſons, which <hi>Gontier</hi> gave in his Sermons in Lent laſt; and then the Prediction of the Provoſt of <hi>Pluviers,</hi> that the King was either ſlain or hurt that day. He was a <hi>Jeſuit</hi> in Faction, and had a Son a <hi>Jeſuit.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To conclude, I think it not amiſs to ſay ſomething concerning the firſt General Council that ever was in the Church of Chriſt; you have the whole Story of it in the <hi>15</hi> Chap. of the <hi>Acts</hi> of the Holy Apoſtles; I ſhall take notice, that it was not called by the particular direction of any of the Apoſtles, but that all of them did con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cur th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>r<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>unto; and this was, doubtleſs, the Method of the Chriſtian Church, during it's greateſt Purity and Integrity; and the truth is, no other way could be uſed, while the Church of Chriſt was under Perſecution: but in proceſs of time, when ſupreme powers did receive, and protect the Chriſtian Faith; and that (as the Scripture ſaith,) Kings and Queens were Nurſing Fathers, and Nurſing Mothers, of the Spouſe of Chriſt; then were General Councils ſummon'd by them, and by them were theſe Councils left to their free De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bates and determinations; whoſe Decrees were afterwards confirm'd by the Supreme Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thorities, whereby thoſe Decrees, which before ſuch a Confirmation did only oblige the Conſcience, had then the Coercive Power of the State to compel their Obſervation; and this Method did continue, till the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſurpation of the Biſhop of <hi>Rome</hi> upon all Powers, both Civil and Eccleſiaſtical; for he now takes upon him to aſſume unto himſelf the power of calling Councils, of preſiding in them, and Confirming their Decrees; ſaying, that with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out His Confirmation, they are invalid. Thus does he make his own Will to be of more Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity than a General Council; and this ſame Will of his to be Superior to all Supreme Powers and Authorities whatſoever: But I ſhall add no more upon this Subject, but proceed to what
<pb facs="tcp:206445:4"/>I at firſt propoſed in the beginning hereof; where I ſhall take notice of ſome things in the <hi>15th</hi> Chap. of the <hi>Acts</hi> of the Holy Apoſtles, where we read of the firſt General Council that ever was in the Church of Chriſt; (and therefore moſt likely to be a direction for all others.) It was occaſioned by an Appeal made by ſome Converted Gentiles, to this General Council; for ſome Phariſaical Chriſtians would impoſe upon theſe Converted Gentiles the whole Law of <hi>Moſes;</hi> therefore to this General Council they do appeal; the words of the Council are theſe. — <hi>The Apoſtles, and Elders, and Brethren ſend Greeting unto the Brethren which are of the Gentiles in</hi> Antioch,<note place="margin">Ver. 23. of this 15. Chap.</note> 
               <hi>and</hi> Syria, <hi>and</hi> Cilicia.</p>
            <p n="24">
               <hi>24. Foraſmuch as We have heard, that certain which went out from us, have troubled You with Words ſubverting Your Souls; ſaying,</hi> Ye muſt be Circumciſed, and keep the Law, to whom We gave no ſuch Commandment:</p>
            <p n="25">
               <hi>25. It ſeemed good unto Us, being Aſſembled with one accord, to ſend choſen Men unto You, with our beloved</hi> Barnabas <hi>and</hi> Paul.</p>
            <p n="26">
               <hi>26. Men that have hazarded their Lives for the Name of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="27">
               <hi>27. We have ſent therefore</hi> Judas, <hi>and</hi> Silas, <hi>who ſhall alſo tell you the ſame things by word of mouth.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="28">
               <hi>28. For it ſeemed good to the Holy-Ghoſt, and to us, to lay upon You no greater Burthen, than theſe neceſſary things.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="29">
               <hi>29. That Ye abſtain from Meets offered to Idols, and from Blood, and from things Strangled, and from Fornication; from which if ye keep your ſelves, ye ſhall do well; fare ye well.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Theſe be the words together; We ſhall now take them into parts. — <hi>The Apoſtles, and Elders, and Brethren,</hi> [There is no Primacy in St. <hi>Peter,</hi> or in any body elſe; either firſt, as to calling this Council; or Secondly, In degree it ſelf; or Thirdly, by way of Confirming this Decree of the Council; Apoſtles, Elders, and Brethren, are all alike concerned;] <hi>Send Greet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, unto the Brethren, which are of the Gentiles in</hi> Antioch, Syria, <hi>and</hi> Cilicia. [Now here I cannot but take notice, that the Church of <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> treats the Churches of <hi>Antioch,</hi> &amp;c. not with a Maternal, but a Fraternal App<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>llation; not like the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> (cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly if ever any had been the Mother-Church, it muſt have been that of <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> St. <hi>Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter,</hi> and all the reſt of the Apoſtles; yea, even a General Council there reſiding,) which makes her ſelf the Mother-Church, and all others ſhe will have to be eſteemed but Her Children; and yet in this General Council St. <hi>Peter</hi> was preſent, as appears by the <hi>7.</hi> Verſe of this <hi>15.</hi> Chap. and yet St. <hi>Peter</hi> does not pronounce any Judgement; contenting himſelf rather with relating matter of Fact; and <hi>Paul</hi> and <hi>Barnabas</hi> do the ſame, as it is Ver. <hi>11.</hi> But the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle St. <hi>James</hi> proceeds further in Ver. <hi>13.14.15.16.17.18.</hi> and in the <hi>19.</hi> Ver. is very bold, ſaying: — <hi>Wherefore my ſentence is, that we trouble not them which from a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong the Gentiles are turned to God;</hi> — and Ver. <hi>20.</hi> He proceeds. — But that we [here St. <hi>James</hi> is equal with St. <hi>Peter,</hi> or any of the reſt] write unto them, that they ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtain from pollutions of Idols, and from Fornication, and from things ſtrangled, and from Blood; — And to this Sentence of St. <hi>James</hi> the whole Council acquieſces, not any one ſpeak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing after St. <hi>James;</hi> [— <hi>Foraſmuch as certain which went out from us, have troubled you with words ſubverting your Souls,</hi> ſaying, <hi>Ye muſt be Circumciſed, and keep the Law,</hi> to whom We, not St. <hi>Peter</hi> alone] gave no ſuch Commandment, it ſeemed good unto <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>s, being aſſembled with one accord; [This Council you ſee was not called by St. <hi>Peter</hi> alone,] to ſend choſen men unto You, with our beloved <hi>Barnabas</hi> and <hi>Paul,</hi> Men that have hazarded their Lives for the Name of our Lord Jeſus Christ; We have ſent therefore <hi>Judas,</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:206445:5"/>and <hi>Silas,</hi> who ſhall alſo tell you the ſame things by word of Mouth; for it ſeemed good to the Holy-Ghoſt, and to <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>s; [you ſee the Holy-Ghoſt is not tyed to St. <hi>Peter's,</hi> or the Pope's Chair, nor the Colledge of Cardinals, but remaining with the General Council;] To lay upon you no heavier burthen than theſe neceſſary things, that ye abſtain from Meats offer'd to Idols, from Blood, and from things ſtrangled, and from Fornication; [all this, the Sentence of, and Opinion of St. <hi>James</hi> delievered to the Council, and thus ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proved of by the Council,] from which if ye keep your ſelves, ye ſhall do well; fare ye well.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="dialogue">
            <pb facs="tcp:206445:5"/>
            <head>A DIALOGUE: BETWEEN <hi>ORTHODOX</hi> a ROYALIST, AND <hi>CACODAEMON;</hi> one Popiſhly affected!</head>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Orthodox,</speaker>
               <p>WELL met, Sir; a Saying of yours I have very often thought of.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Cacodaemon,</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>What is that (Sir) I beſeech you.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ortho.</speaker>
               <p>That the Papiſts are, and always were the Kings beſt Subjects.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Caco.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>I am ſtill of that opinion.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ortho.</speaker>
               <p>If you be ſo, I am deſirous (if your leiſure will permit) that Syſteme of yours may be the Subject of our preſent Diſcourſe. For the truth is, I am of a quite contrary Opinion; this is an aſſured truth, one of us two is out of the way; and good Manners, as well as Charity and good Conſcience, commands us to bring the Knight Errant into the right way; I am ready to hear your Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gument, and I do hope the like patience for mine.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Caco.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>Content, for I am very confident I am in the right; and do hope with little trouble to bring you over to be of my Opinion.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ortho.</speaker>
               <p>Pray, be pleaſed to begin.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Caco.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>I am ready; and thus I begin. Who, I pray, were firmeſt for the late King during his Wars with the long Parliament, were not the Papiſts? This is certain, none of them were of the Parliaments Party; but many thouſand of Proteſtants fought againſt, and at the laſt brought His Sacred Head to the Block; and ſo that Holy Martyr was put to Death by His Proteſtant Subjects. Beſides that, Who were they that Preſerved Our preſent Sovereign in His greateſt Hardſhips, in His greateſt Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tremities, were they not the Papiſts? And none of any Belief whatſoever, I am ſure, are ſo ready as they to ſerve Him now, and to Sacrifice their Lives and Fortunes for Him.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ortho.</speaker>
               <p>I perceive by your ſilence now, that you expect my Anſwer.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Caco.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>I do, but not a Confutation; for what I have ſaid is an Invincible and Infalli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Truth.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ortho.</speaker>
               <p>I hope to make you ſhortly of another Opinion; In the firſt place, I will lay down for an infallible Truth, That never any Proteſtant [<hi>i. e.</hi> a Son of the Church of <hi>England</hi>] did ever draw his Sword againſt the King, or any other their Sovereign Prince, ſince the Reformation, begun by King <hi>Henry</hi> the Eighth.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <pb n="2" facs="tcp:206445:6"/>
               <speaker>Caco.</speaker>
               <p>"Oh <hi>Monſtrum horrendum!</hi> Sure you do not believe what you ſay.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ortho.</speaker>
               <p>Yes, and I'le prove what I ſay, thus; That the late Rebels, <hi>Cromwel</hi> (your Friend Preſident <hi>Bradſhaw</hi>) and the reſt of thoſe that were of their Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, were not Proteſtants, (that is, they were not Sons of the Church of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land;</hi>) you may as well call thoſe People Royaliſts, as Proteſtants, or Sons of the Church of <hi>England;</hi> Did they not overthrow the Hierarchy of the Church, as well as Monarchy? How then can you call them Proteſtants? When indeed they do not deſerve (without a great deal of Charity) the name of Men, ſo Monſtrous were their Actions? Thus much to vindicate Proteſtants, whoſe Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>net is this, that if their Sovereign were a Tyrant, and a <hi>Turk,</hi> (which our So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vereign is far from, I thank God) yet in ſuch a caſe we allow of no other Arms, than what the Primitive Chriſtians did uſe againſt their Perſecutors, that is, Pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers and Tears.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Caco.</speaker>
               <q>Thus far, I confeſs, you have well proved, that Proteſtants in a ſtrict ſenſe ſo called (<hi>i. e.</hi> true Sons of the Church of <hi>England</hi>) may be very good Subjects; and that if they deviate from their Lovalty to their Sovereign, it is not from any ill Principle in their Rel<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>gion, which they ſuck in with their Milk; and that ſuch deviations do rather proceed from the ill Principles of Sin, and frailties of humane Nature; All this I acknowledge for a great truth; but what have you to ſay againſt Papiſts, that they ſhould not be as good Subjects, as any the beſt Proteſtants in the World?</q>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ortho.</speaker>
               <p>In a word, the Rebellion of <hi>Ireland,</hi> accompanied with an univerſal Maſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſacre, without all diſtinction of Ages and Sexes; which as it preceeded the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bellion of <hi>England,</hi> ſo did it alſo exceed it in Inhumanity and Bloodſhed; and, for ought I know, might occaſion the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Rebellion.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Caco.</speaker>
               <q>I did expect no leſs from you, who are ſo great an aſſertor of the Proteſtants, ſo much an adverſary to the Papiſts, and ſo Loyal to the Prince; but all this while I hear nothing of any Principle in the Popiſh Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, that ſhould lead them into ſuch horrid actions, which I do by no means juſtifie.</q>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ortho.</speaker>
               <p>Have patience, and I ſhall give enough of that; you know what our Saviour ſaid, <hi>No man can ſerve two Maſters,</hi> which poſſibly might be a Prophe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy of the Popes Sovereignty over the Kings and Protentates of the World; How can the Papiſts ſerve God, Honor the King, (which two are but one in reality) and Serve, Worſhip, and Obey the Pope? for he is (as our Saviour ſays) the other Maſter.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Caco.</speaker>
               <p>"Well enough; for the Pope (as the Papiſts tell me) pretends to no other Soverelgnty, but in <hi>Spiritualibus.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ortho.</speaker>
               <p>In <hi>Temporalibus</hi> alſo, I aſſure you; and yet it is a wonder, how an O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinion ſo Diametrically oppoſite to the truth of God, delivered in the Scriptures, and the Doctrine of the Antients, both Councils and Fathers, ſhould ever get up among ſuch as profeſs Chriſtianity; And ſurely, were not the Intereſts of the Court of <hi>Rome</hi> in greater eſteem, than the truths of the Goſpel, and the Peace of the Catholick Church, it were not poſſible that your Popes ſhould be ſo pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumptuous as to aſſume this Power; or the Doctors of <hi>Rome</hi> ſo impudent, as to aſſert it. For, to enlarge a little on this particular, of ſuch concernment to the
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:206445:6"/>peace of the Church, and all Chriſtendom; Is it not St. <hi>Peter</hi>'s Exhortation, 1. <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.13. <hi>Submit your ſelves to every Ordinance of Man, for the Lords ſake;</hi> to the King, as Supreme? and St. <hi>Paul</hi> is of the ſame mind, <hi>Rom.</hi> 13.1. <hi>Let e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very Soul be ſubject to the higher Powers;</hi> and <hi>v.</hi> 5. <hi>Wherefore ye muſt needs be ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject, not only for wrath, but alſo for Conſcience ſake;</hi> and St. <hi>Chryſoſtom</hi>'s gloſs upon the Text anſwers all your pretences againſt this truth. <hi>Etiamſi Apoſtolus ſis, &amp;c.</hi> Although you be an Apoſtle, or an Evangeliſt, or a Prophet, yet you muſt be ſubject; And ſuch was St. <hi>Paul</hi>'s own practice; He ſubmits himſelf to the judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of <hi>Felix, Acts</hi> 24; and to <hi>Feſtus;</hi> and from him (<hi>Acts</hi> 25.) makes his appeal to <hi>Caeſar; Appellatio autem non niſi ad legitimum ſit judicem.</hi> And this in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>controulable Power did the Primitive Chriſtians acknowledge in their Emperors, and ſubmit to it; though Heathens, Hereticks, and Perſecutors. <hi>Athanaſius</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing unjuſtly baniſhed from <hi>Alexandria</hi> where he was Biſhop, by <hi>Conſtantius,</hi> and afterwards falſly accuſed of Diſobedience to his Decree, makes this mild de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence to him though an <hi>Arian</hi> and a Perſecutor [<hi>Epiſt. ad</hi> Conſtantium] <hi>Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quaquam reſtiti mandatis tuae Pietatis,</hi> &amp;c. I no way reſiſted the Commands of your Piety; neither ſhall I ever endeavor to enter into <hi>Alexandria,</hi> till your Pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ety give me leave. And thus St. <hi>Auguſtin.</hi> in <hi>Pſal.</hi> 128. <hi>Apoſtata erat</hi> Julia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus, <hi>iniquus, Idololatra; milites tamen Chriſtiani ſervierunt Imperatori,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Julian</hi> was an Apoſtate, a wicked Man, an Idolater; yet the Chriſtians obeyed him: When it concern'd the cauſe of Chriſt, then indeed they acknowledged him only, that was in Heaven; but when the Emperour commanded other things, they o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beyed him. I may alſo ask by what Law the Pope can challenge this Power to himſelf, to diſpoſe of the Temporal Affairs or Eſtates of Princes; Not by any human Law: for the Prince is above the coactive or coercive Power of humane Laws, <hi>ſolo Deo minor:</hi> If by Divine Law, let him ſhew any Text of Scripture, or Tradition of the Apoſtle; ſurely they are both againſt it: <hi>The weapons of our Warfare,</hi> ſaith the Apoſtle [2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 10.] <hi>are not carnal, but Spiritual;</hi> and our Saviour determines againſt it, <hi>Mat.</hi> 20.25.26. <hi>The Princes of the Gentiles ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eriſe Dominion and Authority over them;</hi> but it ſhall not be ſo among you; Hence St. <hi>Hicrom</hi> [Epiſt. 3. ad <hi>Heliodor.</hi>] ſpeaking of the King and the Biſhop, ſaith<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 
                  <hi>Ille nolentibus praeeſt, hic volentibus.</hi> The King hath Power over the refractory and diſobedient; the Biſhop over ſuch as are willing to obey him; His Power compulſory, the Biſhops but precarious. And thus the ſecond General <hi>Nicene Council, Act</hi> 3. diſcourſing of the Regal and Sacerdotal Power, ſpeaks to the ſame purpoſe, <hi>Sacordos Coeleſti<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> curat; Rex autem legibus aequis &amp; juſtis, omma quae in terris ſiunt, procurat;</hi> The Prieſt takes care for what may bring us to Heaven; The King by juſt and equitable Laws orders all Affairs on Earth. And this is anſwerable to the terms and boundaries of both powers which we ſee appointed by <hi>Jehoſaphat</hi> [2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 19.11.] Ananias <hi>the chief Frieſt is over you in all mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of the Lord, and</hi> Zebadiah <hi>the Ruler</hi> [or Prince] <hi>for all the Kings matters:</hi> If therefore the King be over all, and orders all Temporal Affairs by a ſupere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minent and incoercible Authority, none may depoſe him from, or deprive him of his Temporals, either directly or indirectly; much leſs the Church or Pope, whoſe Power is meerly Spiritual; and therefore the behaviours of your Popes have been. Rebellious and Scandalous againſt Reaſon and Religion, againſt the
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:206445:7"/>Doctrine of the Scriptures, and the Practice of the Ancient Chriſtians, eſpecial<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſince <hi>Gregory</hi> the 7th. who ſeems to have been the firſt aſſertor and practi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cant in this intolerable preſumption, not only excommunicating (though that be more than St. <hi>Auguſtine</hi> will allow him,) when he tells us, <hi>nec Rex, nec Mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titudo Excommunicandi ſunt</hi> [<hi>ut-refert</hi> Glaſs. <hi>in</hi> Mat. 23.] but alſo dethroning and depoſing the Emperor <hi>Henry</hi> the 4th. whereof he thus complains; <hi>Ignomini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>am ſuſtinco ante inauditam;</hi> I ſuffer a diſgrace never before heard of: <hi>Vide</hi> Alber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum Stadienſem, <hi>ad Annum</hi> 1106.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Innocent</hi> the Third makes <hi>Otho</hi> (although a Rebel to his Prince) Emperor, and afterwards depoſeth him, not becauſe a Rebel, but becauſe unprofitable to himſelf. <hi>Honorius</hi> the Third Excommunicates <hi>Frederick</hi> the Second, and depoſeth him; which Sentence <hi>Gregory</hi> the Ninth confirms, <hi>Innocent</hi> the 4th alſo. Of the Pride and cruelty of the Popes againſt this Emperor <hi>Frederick;</hi> the King of <hi>France</hi> thus complained (as <hi>Mat. Paris</hi> tells the ſtory, in <hi>Hen.</hi> 3.) <hi>Quo Spiritu, vel auſu temerario Papa.</hi> With what ſpirit, with what daring raſhneſs did the Pope diſinherit, and depoſe from his Imperial dignity, this worthy Prince, than whom a greater is not found among Chriſtians, nor yet his equal, <hi>&amp;c. De tranſgreſſio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nibus ejus, &amp;c.</hi> Concerning his Faults objected, no credit is to be given to his E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemies, among whom the Pope is known to be principal: To himſelf he was al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways an harmleſs and good neighbor; neither have we ever found him faulty in his fidelity concerning Secular Affairs, or the Catholick Faith: We know he was a gallant Souldier in the Holy War, and boldly expoſed himſelf to all dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers both by Sea and Land; I find not ſo much Religion in the Pope, who when he ought to have promoted his Intereſts, and have defended him when he was abroad Fighting Gods Battels, did yet, in his abſence, wickedly endeavor to ſupplant and deſtroy him.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Boniface</hi> the Eighth threatens to depoſe <hi>Philip</hi> King of <hi>France,</hi> abſolving his Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects from their Allegiance, and afterwards ſubjects him and his Kingdom to <hi>Albert</hi> the Emperor.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>John</hi> 23d excommunicates <hi>Ludovicus Bavarus; Benedict</hi> the 12th confirms it; and then <hi>Clement</hi> the 6th depoſeth him.</p>
               <p>I ſhall not trouble you with any more particulars, although I might further tell you of the Kingdom of <hi>Navar</hi> given from the <hi>French</hi> to the King of <hi>Spain</hi> by the Pope; of Our own Kingdoms of <hi>England</hi> and <hi>Ireland</hi> made feodatary to the Popes; ſometimes transferred to the <hi>Spaniard,</hi> other while to the <hi>French;</hi> of ſeveral of our Kings inthralled, our Nation involved in bloody Wars by theſe Papal Uſurpations: But I ſhall conclude, with a Copy of the Grant made by Pope <hi>Alexander</hi> the 6th (Father to <hi>Caeſar Borgia</hi>) of the <hi>Indies</hi> to <hi>Ferdinando</hi> King of <hi>Spain,</hi> and his Heirs for ever; wherein you may read, at large, the pride of the Popes in the Power they pretend to.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Caco.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>I proteſt you aſtoniſh me; I pray be pleaſed to read it over.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Orthod.</speaker>
               <p>I am ready ſo to do; Now I begin.</p>
            </sp>
            <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
               <body>
                  <pb n="5" facs="tcp:206445:7"/>
                  <head>
                     <hi>Alexander,</hi> Biſhop, Servant of the Servants of God; To Our moſt Dear beloved Son in Chriſt, King <hi>Ferdinando,</hi> and to Our Dear beloved Daughter in Chriſt, <hi>Iſabella,</hi> Queen of <hi>Caſtile, Legion, Aragon, Sicily,</hi> and <hi>Granata,</hi> Moſt Noble Princes, Greeting, and Apoſtolical Benediction.</head>
                  <p>AMong other things acceptable to the Divine Majeſty, and according to our hearty deſire, this certainly is the chief, That the <hi>Catholick Faith,</hi> and <hi>Chriſtian Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion,</hi> eſpecially in this our time, may in all places be exalted, amplified, and enlarged, whereby the health of Souls may be procured, and the Barbarous Nations ſubdued and brought to the Faith. And therefore whereas by the favor of Gods Cle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mency (although not with equal deſerts,) We are called to this holy Seat of <hi>Peter,</hi> and underſtanding you to be true Catholick Princes, as we have ever known you, and as your Noble and Worthy Facts have declared, (in a manner to the whole World,) in that with all your ſtudy, diligence, and induſtry, you have ſpared no Travails, Charg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es, or Perils, adventuring even the ſhedding of your own Blood, with applying your whole Minds and Endeavors hereunto, as your Noble Expeditions atchieved in recove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring the Kingdom of <hi>Granata</hi> from the Tyranny of the <hi>Saracens</hi> in theſe our days, do plainly declare your Facts with ſo great Glory of the Divine Name; for the whch, as we think you worthy, ſo ought we of our own free will favorably to grant you all things, whereby you may daily with more fervent Minds, to the Honor of God, and the en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larging the Chriſtian Empire, proſecute your devout and laudable purpoſes, most accep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table to the Immortal God. We are credibly informed, that whereas of late you were determined to ſeek, and find certain Iſlands and firm Lands, far remote and unknown, (and not heretofore found by any other,) to the intent to bring the Inhabitants of the ſame to Honor our Redeemer, and to profeſs the <hi>Catholick Faith;</hi> You have hitherto been much occupied in the Expugnation, and Recovery of the Kingdom of <hi>Granata;</hi> by reaſon whereof you could not bring your ſaid Laudable purpoſe to the end deſired. Nevertheleſs, as it hath pleaſed the Almighty God, the foreſaid Kingdom being reco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered, willing to accompliſh your ſaid deſire, you have not without great Labor, Perils and Charges, appointed our well beloved Son, <hi>Chriſtopher Columbus</hi> (a Man <hi>certes</hi> well commended, as moſt worthy and apt for ſuch a matter) well furniſhed with Men, and Ships, and other neceſſaries, to ſeek by the Sea (where hitherto no Man hath ſailed) ſuch firm Lands and Iſlands far remote, and hitherto unknown, who (by Gods help) making diligent ſearch, in the Ocean Seas, have found certain remote Iſlands, and firm Land, which were not heretofore found by any other; in the which (as is ſaid) many Nations inhabit, living peaceably, and going naked, not accuſtomed to eat Fleſh; and, as far as your Meſſengers can conjecture, the Nations Inhabiting the foreſaid Lands and Iſlands, believe that there is one God, Creator in Heaven, and ſeem apt to be brought to the imbracing of the <hi>Catholick Faith,</hi> and to be indued with good manners; by reaſon whereof we may hope, that if they be well inſtructed, they may ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſily be induced to receive the Name of our Saviour <hi>Jeſus Chriſt;</hi> We are further ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vertiſed, that the forenamed <hi>Chriſtopher</hi> hath now builded and erected a Fortreſs, with good Munition in one of the foreſaid principal Iſlands, in the which he hath pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:206445:8"/>a Garriſon of certain of the Chriſtian Men that went thither with him; as well to the intent to defend the ſame, as alſo to ſearch out other Iſlands, and firm Lands re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mote, yet unknown; We alſo underſtand, that in theſe Lands and Iſlands, is great plenty of Gold and Spices; with divers, and many other pretious things, of ſundry kinds and qualities. Therefore all things diligently conſidered, (eſpecially the amplify<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and enlarging the <hi>Catholick Faith,</hi> as it behoveth <hi>Catholick Princes,</hi> following the Example of your Noble Progenitors of Famous Memory) you have determined by the favour of Almighty God, to ſubject unto you the firm Lands and Iſlands afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaid, and the Dwellers and Inhabitants thereof; and to bring them to the <hi>Catholick Faith.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>We greatly commending this your Godly and laudable purpoſe in our Lord, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſirous to have the ſame brought to a due end, and the Name of our Saviour to be known in thoſe parts; do exhort you in our Lord, and by the receiving of your Holy Baptiſm, whereby you are bound to Apoſtolical Obedience, and earneſtly require you by the bowels of Mercy of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt, that when you intend, for the Zeal of the <hi>Catholick Faith,</hi> to proſecute the ſaid Expedition, to reduce the People of the foreſaid Lands and Iſlands to the <hi>Chriſtian Religion,</hi> you ſhall ſpare no Labors at any time, or be deterred with any perils, conceiving firm Hope and Confidence, that the Omnipotent God will give good ſucceſs to your Godly Attempts; and that being Authorized by the Priviledge of the Apoſtolical Grace, you may the more freely and boldly take upon you the Enterprize of ſo great a matter; We of our own motion, and not either at your request, or at the inſtant Petition of any other perſon, but of out own meer Liberality, and certain Science, and by the fulneſs of Apoſtolical Power, do Give, Grant, and Aſſign to you, your Heirs and Succeſſors, all the firm Lands, and Iſlands, found, or to be found; diſcoverd, or to be diſcovered; towards the <hi>Weſt</hi> and <hi>South,</hi> drawing a Line from the <hi>Pole-Arctick,</hi> to the <hi>Pole Antarctick,</hi> (that is,) from the <hi>North,</hi> to the <hi>South;</hi> containing in this Donation whatever firm Lands, or Iſlands are ſound, or to be found, toward <hi>India,</hi> or toward any other part, whatſoever it be, being diſtant from, or without the foreſaid Line, drawn a Hundred Leagues to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards the <hi>Weſt</hi> and <hi>South</hi> from any of the Iſlands which are commonly called <hi>De Loz Azores,</hi> and <hi>Capo Verd;</hi> All the Iſlands therefore and firm Lands found, and to be found; diſcovered, and to be diſcovered; from the ſaid Line towards the <hi>Weſt</hi> and <hi>South,</hi> ſuch as have not actually been heretofore poſſeſſed by any other Chriſtian King, or Prince until the day of the Nativity of our <hi>Lord Jeſus Chriſt,</hi> laſt paſt, from the which beginneth this preſent Year, being the Year of our Lord, <hi>1493.</hi> Whenſoever any ſuch ſhall be found by your Meſſengers and Captains; We, by the Authority of Almighty God, granted unto us in St. <hi>Peter,</hi> and by the Vicarſhip of <hi>Jeſus Chriſt,</hi> Whoth we bear on the Earth, do for ever, by the tenor of theſe preſents, Give, Grant, Aſſign unto you, and your Heirs and ſucceſſors (the Kings of <hi>Caſtile</hi> and <hi>Legion</hi>) all thoſe Lands and Iſlands, with their Dominions, Territories, and Cities; Caſtles, Towers, Places, and villages, with all the Rights and Jurisdictions thereunto per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taining; Conſtituting, Aſſigning, and Deputing, you, and your Heirs and Succeſſors, the Lords thereof, with full, and free Power, Authority, and Jurisdiction; Decree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing nevertheleſs, by this our Donation, Grant, and Aſſignation, that from no Chriſtian Prince, which actually hath poſſeſſed the foreſaid Iſlands, and firm Lands, unto the day of the Nativity of our Lord aforeſaid, their Right obtained to be underſtood here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:206445:8"/>to be taken away, or that it ought to be taken away. Furthermore, we Command you, in the virtue of Holy Obedience, (as You have promiſed, and as, we doubt not, you will do, upon meer Devotion, and Princely Magnanimity) to ſend to the ſaid firm Lands and Iſlands, Honeſt, Virtuous, and Learned Men, ſuch as fear God, and are able to inſtruct the Inhabitants in the <hi>Catholick Faith,</hi> and good Manners, ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plying all their poſſible diligence in the Premiſſes; We furthermore ſtraightly Inhibit all manner of perſons, of what State, Decree, Orders, or Condition ſoever they be, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though of Imperial Dignity, under the pain of the Sentence of Excommunication, which they ſhall m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ur, if they do the coutrary; that they in no caſe preſume, without ſpecial Licence of you, your Heirs, and Succeſſors, to Travel for Merchandizes, or for any other cauſe, to the ſaid Lands, or Iſlands; found, or to be found; diſcoversd, or to be diſcovered, towards the <hi>Weſt</hi> and <hi>South;</hi> drawing a Line from the <hi>Pole-Arctick,</hi> to the <hi>Pole-Antarctick;</hi> whether the firm Lands, or Iſlands, found, or to be found, be ſcituate towards <hi>India,</hi> or towards any other part, being diſtant from the Line drawn a Hundred Leagues towards the <hi>Weſt,</hi> from any of the Iſlands commonly called <hi>De Loz Azores,</hi> and <hi>Capo Verd;</hi> Notwithſtanding Conſtitutions, Decrees, and A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtolical Ordinances, whatſoever they are, to the Contrary, in Him, from whom Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pires, Dominions, and all good things do proceed; truſting that Almighty God direct<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing your Enterprizes, If you follow your Godly and Laudable Attempts, your Labor and Travels herein ſhall in ſhort time obtain a happy end, with Felicity and Glory of all Chriſtian People. But foraſmuch as it ſhould be a thing of great difficulty, theſe Letters to be carried to all ſuch places as ſhould be expedient; We will, and of like Motion and Knowledge do Decree, that whitherſoever the ſame ſhall be ſent, or where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever they ſhall be received, with the Subſcription of a common Notary thereunto required, with the Seal of any perſon Conſtitute in Eccleſiaſtical Dignity, or ſuch as are Authorized by the Eccleſiaſtical Court, the ſame Faith and Credit to be given thereunto, in Judgment, or elſewhere, as ſhould be exhibited to theſe preſents.</p>
                  <p>Let no Man therefore, whatſoever, Infringe, or dare raſhly to contrary this Letter of our Commendation, Exhortation, Requeſt, Donation, Grant, Aſſignation, Conſtitution, Deputation, Decree, Commandment, Inhibition and Determination; and if any ſhall preſume to attempt the ſame, let him know, that he ſhall thereby incur the Indigna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Almighty God, and his Holy Apoſtles, <hi>Peter,</hi> and <hi>Paul.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <closer>
                     <dateline>Given at <hi>Rome</hi> at St. <hi>Peters,</hi> 
                        <date>in the Year of the Incarnation of our Lord, 1493. The Fourth Day of the Nones of <hi>May,</hi> the firſt Year of our Popedome.</date>
                     </dateline>
                  </closer>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Caco.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">This Arch-Biſhop of <hi>Spalato</hi> did leave the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> and came over to us; but (upon great promiſes of Worldly preferments) return<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed back to his for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer errors, like a Dog to his vomit, or like a<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Sow that is waſhed, to her wallowing in the mire; yet notwithſtanding all this, and fair promiſe of fair uſage, he was burnt by them for an Heretick.</note>
                  <hi>You have made me more than half a Chriſtian; for now I perceive that they (I mean the Papiſts) yield in ſome things to us, till they get us in their clutches, and then with them not to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve at all, (even all their Fopperies) is to believe nothing at all; ſo that in ſuch a caſe (with the Arch-Biſhop of</hi> Spalato) <hi>they will perſecute one with Fire and Sword, if in the leaſt they ſeem to retract; if therefore you have any thing to ſay to confirm me in my new-taken reſolutions, pray proceed; for I am ready to hear you.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <pb n="8" facs="tcp:206445:9"/>
               <speaker>Ortho.</speaker>
               <p>In obedience, Sir, to your lawful deſires, I am ready to give you the ſatisfaction you now require; to add therefore to what I have already urged, I ſhall a little inſiſt upon one particular, in the beginning of our Diſcourſe; and that is, where you plead ſo much, that no Papiſt ever was againſt the Late, or Our preſent King; You are (Sir) now convinced, as you have already declar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed: what therefore I now ſay, is rather to Confirm, than Confute you, becauſe you are now one of us. And thus I begin.</p>
               <p>The Rebellion of the <hi>Iriſh</hi> is already mentioned, therefore no more of that; But I ſhall give you this further inſtance: upon His Majeſties-Reſtauration, it was obſerved, that when the Army (formerly Rebellious) were enjoyned to take the Oaths of Supremacy and Allegiance, that in every Troop of Horſe, and Foot-Company, one Man, or more did refuſe to take thoſe Oaths; at firſt, that refuſal was attributed to the Republicarian or Anti-Monarchical humour, and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition; but upon further inquiry and diſquiſition, it was found out, that thoſe perſons ſo refuſing to Swear, were Papiſts; and more than that, <hi>Roman</hi> Prieſts. And this leads me to another Story, I conceive proper to relate unto you; and that is concerning a ſuppoſed Quaker, under the habit of a Cobler, that was a Tub-Preacher; famous he was a long time during the Rebellion, but by ſome that had been Travellers in Popiſh Countries, was detected to be a <hi>Romiſh</hi> Prieſt, and thereupon was forced to flie.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Caco.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>Sir, I thank you for this addition; this puts me in mind of ſomething of this nature, which (I have heard) was diſcovered by Famous Dr.</hi> Hammond, <hi>which (as I take it) was thus: This worthy Divine was reading a piece of</hi> Chryſoſtom <hi>in a Booksellers Shop, two Men, in the habit of Soldiers, (being in the Shop,) one of them looks over the Doctors ſhoulder into that Book, and turns the</hi> Greek <hi>into</hi> Engliſh, <hi>with as much eaſe as if he had read</hi> Engliſh; <hi>the Doctor being a little ſurprized, turns about to the Tranſlator, ſaying, I did not expect to ſee ſuch a Scholar in that habit; Sir, (ſays the ſeeming Soldier or Fanatick) you are miſtaken, for I am no Scholar; 'tis true, I underſtand all Languages, but that is by the gift of the Spirit, not attain'd un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to by Induſtry, or Humane Learning. Hereupon the Doctor tries him in all Learned Languages, and finds his Soldier exact in all of them; at laſt he tries him in</hi> Welch, <hi>and there the Spirit of Darkneſs forſakes his Diſciple, and leaves him in the dark it ſeems; for at that time (at leaſt) the Church of</hi> Rome (<hi>for this Militant Gentleman was a</hi> Roman <hi>Prieſt</hi>) <hi>wanted a Miracle to underſtand</hi> Welch, <hi>for the ſupport of his Doctrine: ſo Truth overcame a Lye.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ortho.</speaker>
               <p>I have heard that Story you now relate; I am glad to ſee things of this nature ſo well imprinted in your memory: I ſhall ever account our preſent meeting happy, ſince it hath wrought ſo good an effect upon you; What our Saviour enjoyned St. <hi>Peter</hi> upon his Converſion, every perſon ſo Converted is to imitate; When thou art Converted, ſtrengthen thy Brethren, is Our Saviours Precept; and to our Powers we are obliged to obſerve it. And therefore now being diſabuſed your ſelf, I make no doubt but you will diſabuſe others; and ſo (Noble Convert) fare you well for this time.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Caco.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>Pray (Sir) let's not part yet, but give me leave to ask you ſome Queſtions, as concerning the Sacrament, and ſome other things, whereby we may confirm one another in the right Orthodox way.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <pb n="9" facs="tcp:206445:9"/>
               <speaker>Ortho.</speaker>
               <p>I am willing to wait your own leiſure, and give you what ſatisfaction I can; and being you are pleaſed to mention the Sacrament, I will relate to you a Story I met withal lately in a Book of Travails, writ by one who had been a <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſh</hi> Prieſt; In Short, his words are theſe. — One day as I was ſaying Maſs, after the Conſecration of the Bread, being with my Eyes ſhut at the Men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tal Prayer, (which the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> calls her <hi>Memento</hi> for the Dead) there came from behind the Altar a Mouſe, which coming about, came to the very Bread or Wafer-God of the Papiſts, and taking it in his Mouth, ran away with it, not being perceived by any of the People who were at Maſs; for that the Altar was high, and the People below it; but as ſoon as I opened my Eyes to go on with my Maſs, and perceived my God ſtoln away, I looked about the Altar, and ſaw the Mouſe running away with it; which on a ſudden did ſo ſtupifie me, that I knew not well what to do or ſay; I thought if I ſhould take no notice of the miſchance, and any body elſe ſhould I might be queſtioned by the Inquiſition; but if I ſhould call to the People to look for the Sacrament, I might be but chid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den and rebuked for my careleſneſs, which I thought might be more eaſily born, than the rigor of the Inquiſition; whereupon I turn'd my ſelf to the People, and call'd them to the Altar, and told them plainly, that whilſt I was in my <hi>Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mento</hi> Prayers and Meditations, a Mouſe had carried away the Sacrament, and that I knew not what to do, unleſs they would help me to find it out again: the People called the Prieſt that was at hand, who preſently brought in more of his Coat; and as if their God by this time had been eaten up, they preſently prepare to find out the Thief, as if they would eat up the Mouſe, that had ſo aſſaulted and abuſed their God: They lighted Candles and Torches to find out the Malefactor, in his ſecret and hidden places of the Wall; and after much ſearch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and inquiry for the Sacrilegious Beaſt, they found at laſt, in a hole of the Wall, the Sacrament half eaten up, which with great joy they took out; and as if the Ark had been brought again from the <hi>Philiſtines</hi> to the <hi>Iſraelites,</hi> ſo they rejoyced for their new-found God, whom with many Lights of Candles and Torches, with joyful and ſolemn Muſick, they carryed about the Church in Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſion; my ſelf upon my Knees ſhaked and quivered, for what might befall me expecting my Doom and Judgment; and as the Sacrament paſs'd by me, I ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved the marks and ſigns of the Teeth of the Mouſe, as they are to be ſeen in a piece of Cheeſe gnawn and eaten by it. This ſtruck me into ſuch a terror, that I called to my beſt Memory all Philoſophy concerning Subſtance and Acci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent; and reſolved within my ſelf, that what I ſaw gnawn, was not an Accident, but ſome Real Subſtance, eaten and devoured by that Vermin, which certainly was fed and nouriſhed by what it had eaten. Philoſophy well teacheth, <hi>Subſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tia cibi (non accidentis) convertitur in ſubſtantiam aliti;</hi> The Subſtance, (not the Accident of the Food or Meat) is converted and turned into the Subſtance of the thing fed by it and alimented; Now here I know that this Mouſe had fed upon ſome Subſtance, or elſe how could the marks of the Teeth ſo plainly ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear? But no Papiſt will be willing to anſwer, that it fed upon the Subſtance of Chriſts Body; <hi>ergo,</hi> by good conſequence it follows, that it fed upon the Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance of Bread; [and ſo Tranſubſtantiation here in my judgment was confuted by a Mouſe,] which mean and baſe Creature God choſe to convince me of my
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:206445:10"/>former error, and made me now reſolve upon what many years before I had doubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, that certainly the Point of Tranſubſtantiation, taught by the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> is moſt Damnable and Erroneous; For beſides what before I have obſerved, it contradicts that Philoſophical Axiom, teaching that <hi>duo contradictoria non poſſunt ſimul, &amp; ſemel, de eodem verificari,</hi> two contradictories cannot at once and at the ſelf-ſame time time, be ſaid and verified of the ſame thing; but here it was ſo; for here (in <hi>Romes</hi> Judgement and Opinion) Chriſts body was gnawn and eaten; and at the ſame time the ſame Body in another place, and upon another Altar, in the hands of another Prieſt, was not eaten and gnawn; therefore here are two con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tradictories verified of the ſame Body of Chriſt, <hi>viz.</hi> it was eaten and gnawn, and it was not eaten and gnawn: Theſe Impreſſions at that time were ſo great in me, that I reſolved within my ſelf, that Bread really and truly was eaten upon the Altar, and by no means Chriſts Glorious Body which is in Heaven [the Heavens muſt contain him (as it is in the New Teſtament) till his laſt coming,] and cannot be on Earth, ſubject to the hunger and violence of a Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture.</p>
               <p>The ſame Author, upon the finding in a Cave a Heathen Image, worſhipped by the Idolatrous <hi>Indians</hi> for a God, relates this Story.</p>
               <p>In <hi>Mexico</hi> were many of the chief of that place outwardly very fair-tongued, liberal, and very free-handed to the Church, much devoted to the Saints, great Feaſters on their days. and yet in ſecret great Idolaters; but it pleaſed God to make me his Inſtrument to diſcover and bring to light the ſecrecy of their hidden works of Darkneſs; which it ſeems the privacy of a thick Wood, and Mountain, had for many years hid from the Eyes of the World; ſome of theſe being in the company of better Chriſtians, drinking hard of their Drink called [<hi>Chica</hi>] boaſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of their God, ſaying, that he had Preached unto them better than I could Preach; Nay, that he had plainly told them, that they ſhould not believe any thing that I Preached of Chriſt, but follow the old way of their Fore-fathers, who Worſhipped their God aright; but now by the Example of the <hi>Spaniards</hi> they were deluded, and brought to Worſhip a falſe God: The other Chriſtians hearing this, began to wonder, and inquire of them where that God was, and with much ado, promiſing to follow their wayes, and their Gods, got out them the Place, and Mountain, where they might find him; though this in their Cups were agreed up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, yet in ſoberneſs thinking better upon what they had promiſed, they ſlighted what before in drinking they heard; But this was not kept ſo cloſe, but that it came to the Ears of a <hi>Spaniard</hi> in the Valley, who finding himſelf touched in Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience, came to <hi>Mexico</hi> to me, and told me what he heard, that ſome <hi>Indians</hi> of that Town followed an Idol, and boaſted that he had Preached unto them againſt my Doctrine, and for the ways of the former Heathens. I thanked God that he was pleaſed to undermine the ſecret works of Satan, and deſired the <hi>Spaniard</hi> to tell me by whom he came to know of this; He told me the <hi>Indians</hi> Name from whom he had it, and that the ſaid <hi>Indian</hi> was afraid to diſcover the <hi>Indians,</hi> and to tell me of it: I ſent for the <hi>Indian,</hi> who confeſſed unto me before the <hi>Spaniard,</hi> that he had heard ſuch a thing, but knew that if he did diſcover the <hi>Indians,</hi> they, with the power of the Devil, would do him much harm; I told him, if he were a true Chriſtian, he ought to fight againſt the Devil, and not to fear him that could
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:206445:10"/>do him no harm, if God were with him, and he cloſed by Faith with Chriſt; and that the Diſcovery of that Idol might be a means for the converting of the Idola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, when they ſhall ſee the ſmall power of their god againſt the true God of the Chriſtians; I told him plainly, that if he did not tell me who the <hi>Indians</hi> were, and where the Idol was, that I would have him to <hi>Guatalema,</hi> and there make him diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cover what he knew: Here the <hi>Indian</hi> began to tremble, and told me the <hi>Fuentes</hi> had boaſted of ſuch an Idol, whom they called their God, and gave ſome ſigns of a Fountain, and a Pine-tree at the mouth of a Cave in ſuch a Mountain; I asked him if he knew the place, or what kind of Idol it was; he told me that he often had been in that Mountain, where he had ſeen two or three Springs of Water, but never was in any Cave. I asked him if he would go with me, and help me to find it out; He refuſed ſtill, fearing the Idolaters, and wiſhed me not to go, for fear if they ſhould be there, they might kill me, rather than be diſcovered: I anſwe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red him, that I would carry with me ſuch a Guard, as ſhould be able to defend a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt them; and my Faith in the true living God would ſecure me from the falſe god; I am reſolved therefore, with the <hi>Spaniard,</hi> to go to ſearch out the Cave the next day, and to carry with me three or four <hi>Spaniards,</hi> and my Blackmore <hi>Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guel Dalva;</hi> and that <hi>Indian,</hi> I told him I could not ſuffer him to go home to his Houſe that day, for fear he ſhould diſcover in the Town my deſign and purpoſe, and ſo we might be prevented by the Idolaters, who certainly that night would take away their Idol. The <hi>Indian</hi> ſtill refuſed, till I threatned to ſend for the Offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cers of Juſtice, and to ſecure his perſon; with this he yielded; and that he might have no diſcourſe with any body in the Town, nor with the Servants of my Houſe, I deſired the <hi>Spaniard</hi> to take him home to his Houſe, and to keep him there cloſe that day and night, promiſing to be with him next morning; that day I rid to <hi>Pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nola</hi> for the Blackmore, <hi>Miguel Dalva,</hi> and brought him to <hi>Mexico</hi> with me, not telling him what my intent was; I went alſo to four neighboring <hi>Spaniards,</hi> deſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring them to be in readineſs the next morning, to go a little way with me for the Service of God, and to meet me at ſuch a Neighbors Houſe; and that if they would bring their Fowling-Pieces, we might chance to find ſome ſport where we went; and as for proviſion of Wine and Meat, I would provide ſufficiently: They promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed to go with me, thinking that although I told them it was for the Service of God, my purpoſe only was to hunt after ſome wild Deer in the Mountains; I was glad they conſtrued my Action that way, and ſo went home, and provided that Night a good Gammon of Bacon, ſome Fowls roſted, cold, and others boyled, well Pepper'd and Salted, for the next days work; Where I had appointed my <hi>Indian</hi> to be kept, I met with the reſt of my Company, and from thence we went toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to the place of the Idolaters Worſhipping, which was ſome ſix Miles from <hi>Mex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ico,</hi> toward the Town of St. <hi>John Sacate Sacatepeques;</hi> when we came into the Wood, we preſently met with a deep <hi>Barranca,</hi> or Bottom, where was a Running ſtream, which encouraged us to make a diligent Search, but nothing could be found; from thence we aſcended up out of the <hi>Barranca,</hi> and found (after much time ſpent) a Spring of Water, and look'd carefully about it, but could find no Cave: Thus in vain we ſearched till the Evening; and fearing leſt we might loſe our way, and our ſelves, if the Night overtook us, my Friends began to ſpeak of returning homewards; but I conſidering that as yet we had not gone over one
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:206445:11"/>half part of the Wood; and to go home, and come again, might make us to be no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, and ſpoken of; We thought it our beſt courſe to take up our lodging that Night in the Wood, and in that Bottom which we firſt ſearched, where was good Water for to drink, <hi>Chocalatte,</hi> and warm lying under the Trees, and ſo in the Morning to make our ſecond ſearch. The company was very willing to yield un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to it, and the calm Night favored our good Intentions. We made a Fire for our <hi>Chocalatte,</hi> and ſupped exceeding well of our cold Meat, and ſpent moſt part of the Night in merry diſcourſe, having a watchful Eye over our <hi>Indian,</hi> leſt he ſhould give us the ſlip, and committing him to the charge of <hi>Miguel Dalva;</hi> in the Morn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing we Prayed unto God, beſeeching him to guide us that day in the work we went about, and to diſcover unto us the Cave of Darkneſs and Iniquity, where lay hid the Inſtrument of Satan, that ſo by this diſcovery glory might be given unto our true God, and ſhame and puniſhment brought upon his Enemies. We entred a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain into the thick Wood up a ſteepy Hill, and having ſearched all the South ſide of it, we went on to the North ſide, where we found another deep deſcent, which we began to walk down, looking on every ſide, and not in vain; for almoſt half a Mile from the top, we found ſome marks of a Way that had been uſed and trod<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den, which we followed till we came to another Spring of Water; we ſearched narrowly about it, and found ſome pieces of Earthen Diſhes and Pots, and one piece of a Chaffing-diſh, ſuch as the <hi>Indians</hi> uſe to burn Frankincenſe in, in the Church before their Saints; we verily imagined that theſe were pieces of ſome In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruments wherewith the Idolaters performed their duty unto their Idol, and we were the more comforted, for that we new the Earthen Ware had been made in <hi>Mexico;</hi> the Pine-tree, which immediately we diſcovered, confirm'd our hopes; when we came unto it, we made very little more ſearch, for near at hand was the Cave, which was dark within, but light at the Mouth; where we found more Ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then Ware with Aſhes in them, which aſſured us of ſome Frankinceſs that had been burnt; We knew not how far the Cave might reach within, nor what might be in it; and therefore with a Flint we ſtruck Fire, and lighted a couple of Candles, and went in; at the entring it was broad, and went a little forward; but when we were in, we found it turn on the left hand towards the Mountain, and not far; for within two Rods we found the Idol ſtanding upon a low Stool, covered with a Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nen Cloth; the Subſtance of it was Wood, black, ſhining like Jet, as if it had been parched or ſmoaked; the Form was of a Mans Head unto the ſhoulders, without either Beard or Muſtachio's; his look was grim, with a wrinkled Fore-head, and broad ſtartling Eyes; We feared not his frowning look, but preſently ſeized upon him; and as we lifted him up, we found under him ſome ſingle Rials, which his Favorites had offered unto him, which made us ſearch the Cave more diligently; and it was not amiſs, for upon the ground we found more ſingle Rials, ſome Plan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tanes, and other Fruits, Wax Candles half burn'd, Pots of Maize, one little one of Honey, little Diſhes wherein Frankincenſe had been burn'd; whereby I perceiv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the Idolaters and Chriſtians both agree in their Offerings; and had I not been informed that they called this their Idol-god, I could have blamed them no more than the reſt of the Towns, who Worſhip, kneel before, and offer ſuch Offerings to their Saints made of Wood, and ſome no handſomer than was this Idol, which I expected might have been ſome Beaſts ſhape; but being the ſhape and form of a
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:206445:11"/>Man, they might have named him by the name of ſome Saint, and ſo ſome way might have excuſed themſelves, which they could not do, nor would they do it; in that they perſiſted in this Error, that he was their god, and had ſpoken, and Preached unto them; and being afterward asked by me, whether it were the Pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cture of any Saint, ſuch as were in <hi>Mexico,</hi> and other Churches? they anſwered, no; but that he was above all the Saints in the Country. We were very joyful to ſee that we had not ſpent our time in vain; we cut down boughs of Trees, and filled the Cave with them, and ſtopt the Mouth of it up, and came away, making the <hi>Indian</hi> that went with us carry the Idol on his back, wrapped up in Clothes that it might not be ſeen or perceived as he went; I thought it fit to delay the time till Night, and then to enter into <hi>Mexico,</hi> that the <hi>Indians</hi> might ſee nothing; ſo I ſtaid at one of the <hi>Spaniards</hi> Houſes till it were late, and deſired him to warn, from me all the <hi>Spaniards</hi> thereabouts to be at <hi>Mexico</hi> Church the next Sabbath (fearing leſt the Idolaters might be many, and riſe up againſt me) that I had ſomewhat to ſay to them and their Blackmores, concerning their Sodalities; for I would not have them know of the Idol, till they heard of it, and ſaw it in the Church, leſt it ſhould come to the <hi>Indians</hi> hearing, and ſo the Idolaters might ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent themſelves: At night I took my <hi>Indian,</hi> and <hi>Miguel Dalva</hi> with me, and went home; and ſhutting up the Idol in a Cheſt till the next Sabbath, I diſmiſs'd the <hi>Indian,</hi> charging him to ſay nothing, for he knew if he did, what harm might come to him from the Idolaters; and I knew few words would now ſuffice, for that he feared himſelf, if it ſhould be known that he had been with me; I kept <hi>Miguel Dalva</hi> with me, who was deſirous to ſee the end of the buſineſs, and prepared my ſelf againſt the next Sabbath, to Preach upon <hi>v.</hi> 3 of the 20. <hi>Chap.</hi> of <hi>Exodus, Thou ſhalt have none other Gods before Me;</hi> though it were a Text nothing belonging to the Goſpel of the day, from whence commonly, in the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> the Texts, and Subjects, and Sermons and deducted; but I judged that Text moſt ſeaſonable for the preſent occaſion. On the Sabbath-day in the Morning, when the Pulpit was made ready, by him that had care of the Church and Altars, I cauſed <hi>Miguel Dalva</hi> to carry under his Cloak the Idol, and to leave it in the Pulpit, on the ground, that it might not be ſeen, till ſuch time as I ſhould think fit in my Sermon to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce it; and to watch about the Church till the Congregation came in, that none might ſee it, or take it away. Never was there a greater reſort from abroad to that Church, than that day, of <hi>Spaniards</hi> and <hi>Black-Moors,</hi> who, by the warning I ſent unto them, expected ſome great matter from me; and of the Town very few were abſent: The <hi>Fuentes,</hi> and all the reſt that were ſuſpected to be that Idols Favorites (little thinking that their God was brought from his Cave, and now lay hid in the Pulpit to ſhame them) came alſo to the Church. I commanded <hi>Miguel Dalva</hi> to be himſelf near the Pulpit, and to warn thoſe <hi>Spaniards</hi> that knew the buſineſs, and ſome more <hi>Black-Moors</hi> his friends, to be alſo near the Pul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pit-ſtairs.</p>
               <p>Thus, Maſs being ended, I went up to Preach; when I rehearſed the words of my Text, I perceived both <hi>Spaniards</hi> and <hi>Indians</hi> began to look one upon another, as not being uſed to Sermons out of the Old Teſtament: I went on, laying open this Command of God, for having no other gods before him, ſo that the Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine might ſeem to convince all that were there preſent, as well Saint-Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhippers,
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:206445:12"/>as indeed that Idols Worſhippers, if the cauſe of my Preaching upon that Subject had not diverted their eyes from themſelves, to behold their own guiltineſs of Idolatry, and to look only upon thoſe who Worſhipped a piece of Wood for a god, and not as they did for a Saint (which yet in my judgment are much alike.) After I had ſpoken what I thought fit, concerning that horri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Sin, and ſhewed that no creature could have the power of God (who was the Creator of all things) neither could do good or harm without the true liv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Gods Commiſſion, eſpecially inanimate Creatures, as Stocks and Stones, who by the hand and Workmanſhip of man, might have eyes, and yet were dead Idols, and not ſee; might have ears, and not hear; might have mouths, and not ſpeak; might have hands, and not work, nor help and defend with them ſuch as Worſhipped them, and bowed down unto them. Thus having half finiſhed my Sermon, I bowed my ſelf down in the Pulpit, and lifted up the black, grim, and ſtaring Devil, and placed that <hi>Dagon</hi> on one ſide of the Pulpit, with my eyes fixed upon ſome of the <hi>Fuentes,</hi> and others, who I perceived changed their colours, bluſh'd, and were ſore troubled, looking one upon another: I deſired the Congregation to behold what a god was Worſhipped by ſome of them, and all to take notice of him, if any knew what part of the Earth was the Domini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of this god, or from whence he came, I told them that ſome had boaſted that this piece of Wood had ſpoken, and Preached againſt what I had taught of Chriſt, and that therefore he was Worſhipped by them for a god; and they had offered Money, Honey, and of the Fruits of the Earth unto him, and burnt Frankincenſe before him, in a ſecret and hidden Cave under the Earth, ſhewing thereby that they were aſhamed to own him publickly; and that he lurking in the darkneſs of the Earth, ſhewed certainly that he belonged to the Prince of Darkneſs: I challeng'd him there in publick to ſpeak for himſelf, or elſe by his ſilence to ſhame and confound all his Worſhippers; I ſhewed them how being but Wood he had been made and faſhioned by the hands of Man, and therefore was but a dead Idol. I ſpent a great deal of time arguing with him, and defying Sathan, who had uſed him as his Inſtrument, daring the Devil himſelf to take him from that place which I had confined him to, if he could; to ſhew what little power he or Sathan had againſt my Faith in Chriſt; after much arguing and reaſoning, according to the ſhallow Capacity of the <hi>Indians</hi> there preſent, I told them that if their god had power to deliver him from that Execution which I had intend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed againſt him (which was, there publickly to have him cut in pieces and Burnt) they ſhould not believe the Goſpel of Jeſus Chriſt; but if they ſaw no power in him againſt me, the weakeſt Inſtrument of the true living God, then I beſeeched them to be converted unto that true God, who Created all things, and to embrace Salvation by his Son, the only Mediator and Saviour Jeſus Chriſt, and to renounce and abjure from that time all Heatheniſh Idolatry of their Fore-Fathers, aſſuring them for what was paſt I would intercede for them, and ſecure them from what puniſhment might be inflicted upon them by the Preſident and Biſhop; and if they would come to me I would ſpend my beſt endeavors, for the helping and furthering of them in the way of Chriſtianity.</p>
               <p>And thus concluding, without naming any perſon, I went down out of the Pulpit, and cauſed the Idol to be brought after me, and ſending for an Axe, and
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:206445:12"/>for two or three great Pans of Coals, I commanded him to be hewen in very ſmall pieces, and to be caſt into the Fire, and Burnt before all the People in the midſt of the Church: The <hi>Spaniards</hi> cryed out joyfully, <hi>Victor, Victor;</hi> and others repeated, <hi>Gloria à Noſtro Dios,</hi> Glory to our God: The Idolaters held their peace, and ſpake not then a word, but afterwards they acted moſt ſpitefully againſt me, and conſpired day and night to get me at ſome advantage and to kill me; I writ to the Preſident of <hi>Guatalema,</hi> informing of what I had done, and to the Biſhop (as an Inquiſitor, to whom ſuch caſes belong) to be informed from him what courſe I ſhould take with the <hi>Indians,</hi> who were but in part yet diſcovered unto me, and thoſe only by the relation of one <hi>Indian;</hi> from both I received great thanks, for my pains in ſearching the Mountain, and finding out the Idol, and for my zeal in burning of it. And as touching the <hi>Indian</hi> Idolaters, their Counſel to me was, that I ſhould further inquire after the reſt, and diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver as many as I could, and endeavor to convert them to the knowledge of the true God, by fair and ſweet means, ſhewing pity unto them for their great blind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, and promiſing them upon their repentance pardon from the Inquiſition, which, conſidering them to be but new Plants, uſeth not ſuch rigor with them as it uſeth with the <hi>Spaniards,</hi> if they ſhall fall into ſuch horrible Sins: This Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice I followed, and ſent privately for the <hi>Fuentes</hi> to my Chamber, and told them how merciful the Inquiſition was unto them, expecting their converſion and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendment; they ſeemed ſomewhat ſtubborn and angry for that I had burned that god, whom not only they, but many others in the Town, and alſo in the Town of St. <hi>John Sacatepeques,</hi> did Worſhip; I uſed reaſons to perſwade them, no honor was due to it, as unto a God. But one of them boldly replyed, <hi>That they knew it was a piece of Wood, and of it ſelf could not ſpeak; but ſeeing it had ſpoken (as they were all witneſſes) this was a Miracle whereby they ought to be guided, and they did verily believe that God was in that piece of Wood; which ſince the Speech made by it was more than ordinary Wood, having God himſelf in it, and therefore deſerved more Offerings and Adoration than thoſe Saints in the Church, who did never ſpeak unto the People.</hi> I told them, that the Devil rather had formed that ſpeech (if any they had heard) for to deceive their Souls, and lead them to Hell; which they might eaſily perceive, from the Doctrine which I was informed he had Preached againſt Chriſt, the only begotten Son of God, whom the Father loveth, and in whom he is well pleaſed, and againſt whom he certainly would not ſpeak in that Idol. Another anſwered boldly, <hi>Our Fore-Fathers never knew what Chriſt was, until the</hi> Spaniard <hi>came into the Country; but they knew there were gods, and did Worſhip them, and did Sacrifice unto them; and, for ought they knew, this god of theirs belonged in old times to their Fore-Fathers, and theirs was the Old Religion, and Chriſtians were Hereticks and Innovators.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And thus (Sir) you ſee thoſe ſame Arguments made uſe of by theſe Heathens, which the Champions of the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> take up againſt the Proteſtant Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion: For do they not call it an Innovation? Do they not, with theſe Heathens, plead Antiquity? Do they not call us Innovators, as theſe Heathens do the <hi>Spa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niards;</hi> and with them again plead the Religion of their Fore-Fathers; and the Papiſts beſtow the ſame Epithetes upon King <hi>Henry</hi> the Eighth, King <hi>Edward</hi> the Sixth, <hi>Luther, Calvin,</hi> and other Reformers from the errors of the Church
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:206445:13"/>of <hi>Rome?</hi> You ſee, Sir, again, how theſe Idolaters in pleading for their Idol, plead juſt as Papiſts do, for Worſhipping of Saints, which makes it impoſſible for a Papiſt to confute an Idolater: As Popery does alſo by this means prevent the Converſion of the <hi>Jews,</hi> who, however in former Ages much given to Idolatry, are now the greateſt Sticklers againſt it of any People under Heaven.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Caco.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>Sir, I give you many thanks for theſe two Stories; I find my ſelf much edifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by them: the truth is, when you and I firſt met, I did not expect what I now find, and muſt confeſs to you two great Truths; the firſt, that I was inclining you kn<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>w where,</hi> i. e. <hi>to Popery; the ſecond, that your Diſcourſes have made me as firm a Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtant as your ſelf.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ortho.</speaker>
               <p>I give God thanks, with all my heart, for this good progreſs; it ſhall be my Prayer that you may be happy both here and hereafter. Shall we now part?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Caco.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>With your good leave (Sir) let us continue a while together, for if I may not be too troubleſome to you, I would let you know, what I heard urged by a Learn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Papiſt, out of the</hi> Pſalms, <hi>to maintain the Doctrine of Merit, and Interceſſion by Saints to God. Will you givt leave, Sir? For elſe I ſhould not dare to proceed.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ortho.</speaker>
               <p>With all my heart (Sir,) I pray you go on.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Caco.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>The 1 verſe of the</hi> 132 Pſalm <hi>was quoted, the words are theſe,</hi> (Lord, remember <hi>David,</hi> and all his troubles.) <hi>as alſo the</hi> 10 <hi>verſe of the ſame</hi> Pſalm (For thy Servant <hi>David</hi>'s ſake turn not away the preſence of thine Annointed.) <hi>He ſaid this</hi> Pſalm <hi>was compoſed after the Death of King</hi> David, <hi>and therefore con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cludes, that here the Prophet is made an Interceſſor to God: I beg therefore your thoughts, as to this particular.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Ortho,</hi> You ſhall be obeyed; and I do conceive it no difficult matter to anſwer it; and thus I begin: In the firſt place, I know nothing to the contrary, but that this <hi>Pſalm</hi> was compoſed by King <hi>David</hi> himſelf; and though this might ſerve for an an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer, yet, for the preſent, we will ſuppoſe ſome body elſe was the Author of it, af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the Death of King <hi>David.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>All along in the Old Teſtament, we meet with many promiſes for future Times and Ages; the firſt promiſe was to <hi>Adam,</hi> immediately after his fatal Lapſe, where the Meſſiah was firſt of all promiſed; and ſo from time to time, as the Church of God was in any affliction, it was ſupported by promiſes. It would be too long to inſert all thoſe promiſes here; whoever has an inclination to be well acquainted with thoſe promiſes of God to his Church, let him be pleaſed to read the Old Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtament, for the promiſe of the Meſſiah, and other benefits of inferior conſequence; and the New Teſtament, for what concerns Chriſtianity. King <hi>David</hi> (whom, in this <hi>Pſalm, Romes</hi> Stickler would make an Interceſſor between God and Man) had many promiſes (as <hi>Adam,</hi> and others) made unto him, beneficial to the Church of God; therefore when the Church (or Servants of God) was in any ſtreights, God was thereupon minded of his promiſes; not that God ſtood in need of theſe <hi>Memorandums;</hi> but hereby the Church, <hi>i. e.</hi> the Faithful Servants of God, did ſupport themſelves and their Holy Faith, with the remembrances of theſe promiſes of God to King <hi>David</hi> and others; and ſo we Chriſtians are ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ported, in our greateſt exigencies, with this promiſe of Chriſt to his Church, that
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:206445:13"/>the Gates of Hell ſhall not be able to prevail againſt it; and therefore whoever thinks theſe two Verſes (the firſt, and the tenth) of this <hi>Pſalm,</hi> to confirm the <hi>Romiſh</hi> Doctrine of praying to Saints, and making them Interceſſors, is very much miſtaken; for (ſays our Saviour) <hi>Come unto Me</hi> [this <hi>Me</hi> has an Emphaſis in this place] <hi>all ye that labor and are heavy laden, and I will refreſh you;</hi> in another place, ſays our Saviour, —<hi>I will pray unto the Father for you;</hi> what need we then to deſire the interceſſion and mediation of any other than Jeſus Chriſt, the Saviour, Mediator and Interceſſor, of and for the whole World? And, as it is in the 130. <hi>Pſalm,</hi> the laſt Verſe, <hi>And He ſhall redeem</hi> Iſrael <hi>from all his Sins.</hi>—He it is only can do it, and not Saints or Angels, who are but our fellow Creatures, and did evermore refuſe Worſhip and Adoration, wherever it was offered unto them; many inſtances of this we have both in the Old and New Teſtaments.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Caco.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>I do confeſs I have very much treſpaſſed upon your patience; one word more, Sir, and I have done; there is one thing urged by the Papiſts, which does a little weigh, and that is this; —the Papiſt urges thus againſt the Proteſtants,</hi> You <hi>(ſay they to the Proteſtants)</hi> do acknowledge that Papiſts may be Saved, <hi>i. e.</hi> that there is Salvation in our Church; we hold <hi>(ſays the Papiſts)</hi> that there is no Salvation out of the Pale of the <hi>Roman</hi> Church; therefore to be a <hi>Roman</hi> Catholick, as it is the beſt, ſo it is the ſafeſt Religion that is. —<hi>I beſeech you, Sir, do not miſtake me, I do not (I aſſure you) ſpeak this as being of their perſwaſion, but to be better enabled by you to oppoſe our Adverſaries, when they ſhall object to us this fallacious ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gument.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ortho.</speaker>
               <p>Sir, you ſhall not want what I can contribute to your ſatisfaction; and truly I think this may be eaſily anſwered; and I ſhall begin with a reply. I have heard of a very learned man upon this Subject, in a Diſputation between him and a Papiſt; who being at his laſt ſhift, and forced to make uſe of your above<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaid Argument, anſwered thus, —<hi>Sir,</hi> ſays he, <hi>do not condemn us for an exceſs of Charity towards you, and conſider how want of Charity in you towards us may be laid to your charge another day.</hi> And withall, take notice of this, that in the ſame manner thoſe infamous Schiſmaticks, the Donatiſts, argued againſt St. <hi>Auſtin</hi> and the Catholick Church, taking hold of their Confeſſion, that Salvation might be had in their Churches, which was not (ſaid theſe Schiſmaticks) to be had in a Catholick Church; thus did theſe wicked Schiſmaticks conclude (with the Papiſts) their Religion to be the ſureſt and ſafeſt; and ſo conſequently, the beſt alſo: Doth not the King of <hi>Aſſyria,</hi> by his Servants, rant, and argue againſt good King <hi>Hezekiah,</hi> much at this rate, in the 2 of the <hi>Kings,</hi> and the 18 Chap. <hi>Have any of the gods of the Nations at all delivered his Land out of the Hand of the King of</hi> Aſſyria? <hi>Where are the gods of</hi> Hamath, <hi>and of</hi> Arphad? <hi>Where are the gods of</hi> Sepharvaim, Henah, <hi>and</hi> Ivah? <hi>Have they delivered</hi> Samaria <hi>out of my Hand? Who are they Amongſt all the gods of the Countries, that have delivered their Country out of my Hand, that the Lord ſhould deliver</hi> Jeruſalem <hi>out of my Hand?</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Caco.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>One word more (Sir) and I promiſe you I have done: Does not the Author of whom you quote the Story of the Speaking Idol,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>expreſs an averſion againſt, and relate ſome things to the prejudice of Arch-Biſhop</hi> Laud, <hi>towards the Concluſion of his Book.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <pb n="18" facs="tcp:206445:14"/>
               <speaker>Ortho.</speaker>
               <p>I confeſs he does, and he is blame-worthy for it; but withal to be pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyed, if you conſider his caſe aright; and thus it is; in his Infancy, with his Milk, he ſucks in the <hi>Roman</hi> Religion, has his Education in Popiſh Countries, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comes a Prieſt, goes over an Emiſſary into the <hi>Indies,</hi> for the advancing and propagating the <hi>Romiſh</hi> Religion: However, being a Man of Parts, and Learn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, through all the Miſts and Clouds of Error, he diſcerneth the unreaſonable<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs firſt, and then the dangerous Tenets of the Church of <hi>Rome;</hi> but all this while, it is ſcarce much more than Break of day with him; he is but a Negative Chriſtian, but a <hi>Neophyte;</hi> the <hi>Roman</hi> Religion he perceives is bad, but as yet knows little of the Proteſtant Religion: Thus endowed, he comes over into <hi>En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gland,</hi> very little before our Civil Wars began; ſtill troubled in mind, he goes over into <hi>Italy</hi> to <hi>Rome,</hi> where he thought, if any place could afford him ſatis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faction in the <hi>Romiſh</hi> Perſwaſion, there it muſt be; in that place he converſes with Eminent Divines, who tell him ſtrange Stories of the Arch-Biſhop of <hi>Can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terbury</hi> his great inclination to return to the <hi>Roman</hi> Church; This <hi>Neophyte,</hi> this doubting, wavering Chriſtian, is told theſe falſhoods by theſe <hi>Roman</hi> Divines, to encourage him to go over an Emiſſary into <hi>England,</hi> and there labour vigorouſly in the <hi>Roman</hi> Vineyard; the poor Man believes that which theſe men knew to be falſe; but this muſt be rumor'd, to gain <hi>Engliſh</hi> Proſelytes, (you know, how much the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> allows of officious and beneficial Lyes) confirm thoſe they have, and add Reputation to their Cauſe amongſt the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Papiſts, [and obſerve (Sir) do not the Papiſts the ſame thing now? Do they not obſerve the ſame Method ſtill, to the great dis-heartening His Majeſties Proteſtant Subjects, ſo that the King and Parliament have been forced to take notice of their Inſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lencies?] Well, Sir, with this prejudice to the Proteſtant Church of <hi>England,</hi> and the Arch-Biſhop, This <hi>Neophyte,</hi> this doubting Chriſtian, comes over into <hi>England,</hi> where every innocent Ceremony, and the Liturgy of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> confirm in him the Belief of the <hi>Italian</hi> Falſhoods concerning the Arch-Biſhop, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and by reaſon of that his perſwaſion, he proves as great an Enemy to the Church of <hi>England,</hi> as of <hi>Rome;</hi> and thus out of the Frying Pan, or out of one Fire, he leaps into another; and ſo turns a new kind of Fanatick; and it often falls out, that out of one extream, Men are apt to run into another; and therefore it often falls out, that when a Proteſtant turns Papiſt, he, for the moſt part, does throw himſelf into the Arms and Boſom of a Jeſuite, and then ſucks in all their wicked and abominable practices; as principles againſt the Sovereignty of Kings, Humane Society, and Moral Virtues, and the Dictates of Nature; a ſtout Champion of the Pope, and Court of <hi>Rome,</hi> (rather than the Church of <hi>Rome</hi>) againſt all Temporal and Civil Intereſts whatſoever, you may be ſure ſuch a Convert he proves; and truly, this is ſo natural to Man, in avoiding one Rock of danger and offence, to fall foul upon another; that if Men be not very wary and diſcreet, they can hardly avoid it: (thus when a Papiſt turns Proteſtant, he is apt to turn from being that, to throw himſelf headlong into all ſorts of En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thuſiaſtick phrenſies, in oppoſition to Popery:) this was the caſe of this Author; for he was ſo fearful of the Rock of Popery, that he fell foul upon the Rock of Enthuſiaſm, and there made Ship-wrack of his Faith; and therefore waving that paſſage concerning the Arch-Biſhop, and Monarchy, let us believe the reſt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:206445:14"/>the Idol, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> for he delivers them upon his own knowledge, being an Eye<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>witneſs, and not reports from others; and now, thus I have, Sir, I hope, anſwered your Scruple concerning this Author.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Caco.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>I do confeſs, you have very fully; and now I will give you no further trouble at this time; yet, if it be not too troubleſome to you, be pleaſed to let a ſmall piece, of ſome two ſheets of Paper, conclude our Diſcourſe.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ortho.</speaker>
               <p>Name it. Sir, and you ſhall be obeyed.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Caco.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>It is that which you ſhewed me lately; the Title of it is this:</hi> [An Anſwer to a Pamphlet, Entituled (The humble Apology of the <hi>Engliſh Catholicks</hi>) written by a Royaliſt, before Chriſtmas.]</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ortho.</speaker>
               <p>I'am ready to obey you, and thus I begin; and firſt with the Title, though I but repeat your foregoing words.</p>
            </sp>
            <q>
               <floatingText xml:lang="eng">
                  <body>
                     <div type="answer">
                        <head>An Anſwer to a Pamphlet, Entituled [<hi>The humble Apology of the</hi> Engliſh Catholicks,] Written by a Royaliſt, before Chriſtmas, <hi>1666.</hi>
                        </head>
                        <epigraph>
                           <bibl>
                              <hi>Thuanus.</hi>
                           </bibl>
                           <q>Miſeros Principes quibus de conjuratione non creditur, niſi occiſis.</q>
                        </epigraph>
                        <p>IF the Author of the Apology could make good the beginning of his Diſcourſe, I could very heartily turn Apologiſt for him and his Friends. He ſays aright (and the Devil ſpake true, when he cry'd aloud, that <hi>Jeſus was the Son of God</hi>) that the Arms which Chriſtians may uſe againſt Lawful powers, in their Severities, are only Prayers and Tears: Thus far he ſpeaks like a Proteſtant, that is to ſay, a Primitive Chriſtian; and it might have ſtood as a fair Character of his pretended Innocency, had he not foully beſpattered it in the Sequel, with the Dirt he caſts upon the face of Authority. But firſt, It would be conſidered what it is the Apolo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſt would be at, upon his frequent Compellation of his Lords and Gentlemen; is it to draw them to a firm Combination with thoſe of his <hi>Roman</hi> party, againſt all ſuch as ſhould queſtion the innocency of his Carriage and Intentions? Nothing leſs, it ſeems, can ſatisfie or ſecure him, unleſs my Lords and Gentlemen, that is, the old conſtant Royaliſts, ſtand up for his Advocate, he muſt fall under the heavy cenſure of his greateſt Adverſaries, who (to complete the miſchief and miſery of it) are not only become his Accuſers, but his Inſulting Judges, as he com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plains.</p>
                        <p>And now it is high time for my Lords and Gentlemen to remember their often Vows to that party, and Renounce all further Conjunction with them that have been the cauſe of ſo great Calamity to the Nation, as he there tells them.</p>
                        <p>But is not this — <hi>Davide &amp; Impera?</hi> and though they did not nip the Plant in the Bud, yet now being grown up, and not likely to anſwer them in the expected Fruits, they will endeavor ſo to diſmember the parts, as may manifeſtly endanger the whole.</p>
                        <p>For what elſe mean thoſe words, <hi>Let it never be Recorded in Story, that you forgot your often Vows to us, injoyning to them</hi> (thoſe inſulting Judges, as he terms them be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore) <hi>that have been the cauſe of ſo great Calamity to this Nation.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <pb n="20" facs="tcp:206445:15"/>
                        <p>Is not a Diſ-union here manifeſtly endeavored? and that in direct contradiction to what was before proteſted, [far be it from Catholicks to perplex Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments.] To reconcile this difference in the expreſſions, will well become the Apologiſt, before he anſwer the following Objections, which he makes his next task.</p>
                        <p>And here firſt he preſents his Catholick Party, aſtoniſhed even to admiration, at that Calumny above the reſt, that their Principles are ſaid to be inconſiſtent with Government, and they themſelves thought ever prone to Rebellion; as if, becauſe they account themſelves the only Orthodox Chriſtians, they muſt neceſſarily be ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry loyal Subjects at the leaſt.</p>
                        <p>Indeed, If they could make good the former, we had reaſon to expect ſome com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pliance, as to the latter;<note place="margin">Religio à religan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>do.</note> ſeeing Religion hath its name from the Connexion and ſtrick conjunction it works in its Profeſſors, as with each other, ſo in all with that government, and Governors under which they have their common protection.. But how Orthodox and united <hi>Roman</hi> Catholicks are in the grounds of their Belief (the main Ingredient in the Eſſence of Religion) hath ſufficiently appeared in the Writings of many, who have unanſwerably evinced the nullity of the <hi>Romaniſts</hi> Faith; whether ultimately reſol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved into their virtual Church, the Pope with his Conclave, as the Jeſuites will have it; or into the repreſentative Church, a General Council, as others will have it; or into both the former conjoyned, as others contend; or <hi>(erranti nullus terminus)</hi> into the new mode of Oval Tradition, as it is lately, and clamorouſly, urged by o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, who abominate the former.</p>
                        <p>Yet though our Catholicks do thus ſtagger in the Grounds of their Faith, are they not more firm in their Fealties and Loyalties? Surely their Principles are every way conſiſting with the Government under which they live.</p>
                        <p>Nothing leſs; and it will plainly appear, if we conſider the Doctrine of their Church, and their frequent practice; to the former, much need not be ſaid; that the Pope, the acknowledged Head of their Church, hath a plenary power to Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>communicate all Chriſtian Kings that will not cloſe with Papal Perſwaſion; and when they are Excommunicated, that they ceaſe to be Kings; that their Subjects are abſolved from all Fealty and Allegiance to them; yea, may take up Arms a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt them, and ſo murder them: All this is ſo notoriouſly known, that as no re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al <hi>Roman</hi> Catholick will deny, ſo it were needleſs to urge further proof of it; He that hath leiſure may find enough of this,<note place="margin">Becanus, Bellar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine, Roſſius, Molina, Campion, Stapleton, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                           </note> in <hi>Alvarez, Mariana,</hi> and others, that ſpeak expreſly enough at this rate; and hath it not been ſufficiently verified in the <hi>Roman</hi> Catholicks practice? 'tis well known, who encouraged one <hi>Parry</hi> to Murther Queen <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lizabeth;</hi> what Pope it was that iſſued out his dreadful Excommu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nication, animating the Subjects of <hi>England</hi> againſt her; and, if you will allow of Cardinal <hi>Perron's</hi> poſitive Sentence, he will tell you, that that Doctrine which renders Kings indepoſable, opens a gap to no leſs than Schiſm, and Hereſie; and hereby, as if it were not only Lawful, but neceſſary, to ſuppreſs whatever they be, that will not Conform to the Popiſh Hierarchy.</p>
                        <p>He that ſhould ſee a Sovereign Prince holding the Baſon, whilſt the Pope waſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth his Hands; and another, no leſs Sovereign, holding his Stirrup (though unfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunately
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:206445:15"/>miſtaken in the ſide,) whilſt he mounts up on Horſe-back; yea, he that ſhould ſee that Biſhop of <hi>Rome</hi> treading on a great Princes neck, and abuſing that of the <hi>Pſalmiſt,</hi> for juſtification of his uſurped power; <hi>Super Leonem &amp; aſpidem,</hi> &amp;c. cannot but conclude, that, <hi>Dominus Deus noſter Papa</hi> (as the Canoniſts ſtile him) will be Supream Prince of the Chriſtian World; and that all other Potentates muſt limit their Authority, and Jurisdiction, according to the meaſure of his <hi>Placet.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>And now, the Premiſes conſidered, that upon the Popes excommunication, Kings ceaſe to be ſuch, and ſtand lawfully expoſed to all inſolencies of their Subjects, (as hath already appear'd,) I cannot but very much wonder, that the <hi>Romaniſts</hi> ſhould be ſo angry with <hi>Cromwel, Bradſhaw,</hi> and the reſt of that helliſh Crue, for Murthering our late Sovereign of Bleſſed Memory; were they not taught by thoſe <hi>Romiſh</hi> Fathers, above cited, to Murther <hi>Charles Stuart,</hi> and yet not kill the King? I dare boldly ſay, that our late Republicarians have not one Tenet that is deſtructive to Civil Government, and the Sovereignty of Kings, that was not firſt broached by the <hi>Romaniſts,</hi> to whom we owe our late Confuſions, which hath anſwered the Predictions of <hi>Gondamore,</hi> the <hi>Spaniſh</hi> Embaſſador, who, when he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turned to <hi>Spain,</hi> gave out, that he had kindled a Fire in <hi>England,</hi> which would burſt out Forty Years afterwards.</p>
                        <p>Not to inſiſt upon thoſe ſeveral diſguiſes preſented by the <hi>Romaniſts,</hi> in the late Troubles, under the habit of all ſorts of Mechanick Artiſts, Soldiers and others; ſo to Preach up and foment the Rebellion, with our home-bred Sectarians; this may ſuffice to demonſtrate how ill-conſiſtent their Principles are with our <hi>Engliſh</hi> Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment; and conſequently how weakly they acquit themſelves of that Calumny they complain of, even to Admiration; but the <hi>Apologiſt</hi> hath his other pretences, and will clear all Objections that may encounter him in his way; it will be neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry to take a brief view of them. And here, firſt, our Author accuſeth us with a pretended Submiſſion to Lawful Powers; begins then to boaſt how patiently their party did bear with the proceedings of the preſent Parliament; how they uſed no tricks and ſubterfuges to nip their proceedings in the bud; (this is his expreſſion,) and I would be glad to know what they could have done more than they did? what means he by this nipping in the bud? would he have another Gun-Powder Treaſon? to what purpoſe is all this enumeration of our ſeveral Kings, <hi>Richard</hi> the Firſt, <hi>Ed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward</hi> Longſhanks, <hi>Edward</hi> the Third, and <hi>Henry</hi> the Fifth, their Opinions of their Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſh Subjects; in the firſt place, it may be ſaid, that were not ſo clear-ſighted, as Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces are in theſe days; that the Roman Writers were not altogether ſo inſolent, plain, and poſitive againſt the Sovereignty of Kings, as now.</p>
                        <p>As for the <hi>French</hi> Kings, they did very roundly maintain their Rights and Sove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reignties, having been ſufficiently tormented by their Popiſh Subjects in the time of the League; that what the Jeſuites were inventing to the prejudice of Kings, was by cunning and inſinuation; Writing one thing, and making the <hi>French</hi> Kings believe another, as is uſual with that kind of people.</p>
                        <p>As for the Houſe of <hi>Auſtria,</hi> they have the greateſt dependences upon the Pope imaginable, and the Pope hath a very great tie upon that Houſe; for by their Inceſtuous Marriages, authorized by the Popes, they make it impoſſible for them to throw off the Authority of the Pope; for ſhould they do ſo, all of the
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:206445:16"/>Houſhold would prove Baſtards; and now even in theſe our days, the preſent King of <hi>Poland,</hi> (in the life-time of his Brother, known by the name of Cardinal <hi>Caſimir,</hi>) did Marry his ſaid own Brothers Wife; and this was the Policy of the Pope with our <hi>Henry</hi> the Eighth, in diſpenſing with his Marrying his own Bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers Wife, that he might have as great Dominion over the Kings of <hi>England,</hi> as of <hi>Spain.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>As for the Authors branding this laſt Century, that what was perpetrated now, was never done before (as to <hi>Mary</hi> Queen of <hi>Scots,</hi> and Our late Sovereign,) I very much wonder at the Impudence of the Man, to mix theſe two actions; the firſt was done by Lawful Authority; for her being Queen of <hi>Scotland,</hi> did not be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reave Queen <hi>Elizabeth</hi> of her Sovereignty; and I have heard it averr'd by Learn'd and knowing Men, that the King of <hi>Scotland</hi> hath ſate in an <hi>Engliſh</hi> Parliament in former ages, as a Peer of <hi>England;</hi> and then no wonder, nor Injuſtice neither, that the Queen of <hi>Scotland</hi> ſuffered Death for her Treaſons againſt the Queen. As for the latter, (the Murther of our late Sovereign of Bleſſed and Glorious Memory,) the action is without Example, ſuch and ſo hainous a thing was never acted upon the Theatre of the World: And as I ſaid before, ſo I will again, that the Murther of that good King may properly enough be ſaid to be the abominable product of that accurſed Doctrine of the Popes Infallibility, and his Sovereignty over Kings; for thoſe accurſed Regicides, and Murtherers of that Glorious King, did but a lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle alter the Argument; for that Power which the Romaniſts lodged in the Pope, theſe wicked Miſcreants placed in the People; They had heard there was a Pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er above Kings, and inſtead of giving it to the Pope, they gave it to the Peoples Repreſentative, and ſo fell that Great King, to the Conſternation of the whole World, and for a <hi>Memento</hi> to all Kings, to awake them out of their Lethargy, and be an Exhortation to them to Vindicate their Supreme Authority: We do all of us much commend the Fidelity of <hi>Carlos Whitegrave,</hi> and the <hi>Penderels,</hi> and <hi>Huddle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtone;</hi> and this Author is much miſtaken, if he think we wiſh any of them ill: We have ſaid enough already to evidence, that they effected that glorious and happy action, (happy, I ſay, to theſe Nations,) through ſome other inſtigations, than the Principles of the Romiſh Religion; they were led thereto certainly by a hand Divine, as well as aſſigned by it; they carried <hi>Engliſh</hi> hearts about them at that time; but if they will Apoſtatize, 'tis none of my fault, for my part, I am well con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent they be diſpenſed with, as a Mark put upon them for their miraculous preſerving our Good King.</p>
                        <p>As for the ſtigmatized perſon, I muſt needs ſay for him, that he labored in the Vineyard before the laſt hour of the day, and was very ready, both with Hand and Pen, to promote the Intereſts of the King for his Reſtauration; and therefore that word of reproach might well have been left out.</p>
                        <p>That we differ in Religion, is but too true; and we dare as boldly as your ſelves appeal to the day of Judgement; ſomething, you ſay, we differ; I ſay, very much; elſe why does Your Church Damn ours? But this is not a place, either to Diſpute about Religion, or expreſs wherein we vary; We are aſſured our Religion is the beſt, free from Superſtition, free from too much homelineſs, God and the King are beſt ſerved in our way; Our Church is Monarchical as well as yours, but ſtill with a Subordination to Our Sovereign, Temporal Prince; what our great Ance<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtors
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:206445:16"/>were, we ſhall not be aſhamed to remember, nor the Converſion of <hi>England</hi> from Paganiſm, which poſſibly (as all the World beſides Converted from the like Errors,) did retain ſome few Pagan Ceremonies, from which the Church of <hi>England</hi> was purified in the Reformation of <hi>Edward</hi> the Sixth, and Queen <hi>Elizabeth:</hi> He does well to put us in mind of <hi>Romiſh</hi> Perſecutions; Are not we juſtified thereby, if we do the ſame to you? <hi>France,</hi> forſooth, is inſtanced, where the Reformed Religion is permitted; which I ſhall leave indifferent whether to attribute that toleration to their vaſt numbers, or to the innocency of their Tenets, not at all prejudicial to Kings: This I am ſure, they own no Sovereign above their natural King; they have no Forreign Juriſdictions in their Spirituals, and as little in their Temporals; Let this be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membered, they aſſiſted their King <hi>Henry</hi> the Third againſt his Popiſh Rebels, even after the Maſſacre at <hi>Paris;</hi> and <hi>Henry</hi> the Fourth, in his Siege of <hi>Paris,</hi> when the Duke of <hi>Parma</hi> reliev'd it. But as for the <hi>French</hi> King, he is no com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petent inſtance in this caſe; (had you ſingled out ſome <hi>Trent</hi>-Catholick, ſuch our <hi>Engliſh</hi> Catholicks would be acknowledged,) there had been a fairer colour for your Argument. When you have found ſome <hi>Roman</hi> Catholick of the <hi>Trent</hi>-Perſwaſion, allowing the ſame favours to known Proteſtants, you may more plauſibly plead for the like allowance; till when, by their Inquiſitions, and ſuch like entertainments of Proteſtants, they have preſcribed the Law for other Princes towards thoſe, that no leſs differ from them in matters of Religion. We will wave the Maſſacre at <hi>Paris,</hi> to come nearer home; What think you of the Maſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſacre in <hi>Ireland?</hi> As a fore-runner of the <hi>Enliſh</hi> Troubles; Was not the Maſſacre and Rebellion in <hi>Ireland</hi> countenanc'd and own'd by a Popes <hi>Nuncio?</hi> Let us draw nearer to theſe times, and ſpeak of what paſs'd within this Twelve Months: Was not the Popes Bull an occaſion of Cornet <hi>Nangle</hi>'s Rebellion, which had been as univerſal as the firſt, but that the <hi>Romiſh</hi> Party there wanted ſtrength; the Author by mentioning the <hi>French</hi> King's kindneſs to the <hi>French</hi> Proteſtants, puts me in mind to affirm, he is much miſtaken; for that King hath of late be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gun very much to Perſecute them; he has taken from them moſt of their Churches, will not ſuffer them to Educate their own Children, and many other grievous puniſhments he does now inflict upon them; and it may well be ſuſpected, he in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tends yet more againſt them, having already purged his Guards of all of their Belief.</p>
                        <p>The Author grows yet more Impudent, and Extravagant; for firſt, he goes about to Illegitimate Queen <hi>Elizabeth,</hi> and then beſpatters the Fame of Our King <hi>Henry</hi> the Eighth; and by that, one may ſee where he has his Breeding, and where he learned to ſpeak contumeliouſly of Kings.</p>
                        <p>You urge the Allegiance ſworn to Queen <hi>Mary;</hi> and 'tis no ſuch wonder, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidering the Artiſices and Power of the <hi>Roman</hi> Catholicks at that time: But all <hi>Roman</hi> Catholicks will grant, that Queen <hi>Maries</hi> Mother was King <hi>Henry</hi>'s Bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers Wife; yes, and it will be reply'd, that the Pope diſpenſed with the Marri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>age. He did ſo, but St. <hi>John</hi> the Baptiſt (whom Our Bleſſed Saviour Honours with ſo high a Teſtimony in the Goſpel) would not have done it; He condemn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the like Marriage in King <hi>Herod;</hi> and had he liv'd in thoſe times, would have done no leſs in King <hi>Henry,</hi> though perhaps the Pope, like another <hi>Herod,</hi> would
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:206445:17"/>have cut off his Head for that bold affront; yet the Popes Power, though never ſo much ſevere in thoſe times, could not then ſilence the ſuffrages of our Uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſities here, nor thoſe in forreign parts, who joyntly affirm'd and confirm'd both the lawfulneſs, and neceſſity of King <hi>Henry</hi>'s Divorce from his Brothers Wife; which doth ſufficiently wipe off that filth the Author from his Impure mouth breaths out againſt that Queen of Glorious Memory: But King <hi>Henry</hi> the Eighth, it ſeems, is a great Eye-ſore to you, and you will leave no place unſearch'd for ſome Stones of Reproach to throw at him; yet if you would be pleaſed to caſt a ſerious Eye upon divers of your Popes, the chief Heads of your Church, (you may find a full choice, in the Ninth and Tenth Centuries, beſides ſeveral others;) and when you have throughly peruſed the exact Symetry of their carriage and practices, (as deſcribed in ſome of your own Authors,) then turn your Eye upon King <hi>Henry</hi> the Eighth, and you will readily, I doubt not, conclude the Saint to be on his ſide; and making ſo bold with Princes, it would be a wonder, if Miniſters of State did eſcape his Pen; and it may well be affirm<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, that King <hi>James</hi> is wounded through <hi>Cecyl</hi>'s ſide, or rather that wiſe King himſelf is deeply pierc'd; for may not one thus underſtand the <hi>Apologiſt? Cecyl</hi> is compared to <hi>
                              <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>lyſſes,</hi> and King <hi>James</hi> to <hi>Cromwel,</hi> the whole Parliament is like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe aſperſed by him; and according to the opinion of the <hi>Apologiſt,</hi> God is mocked every Fifth of <hi>November;</hi> ſo that God himſelf cannot eſcape him neither.</p>
                        <p>He inſiſts upon the merit of thoſe of his Religion that ventured their Lives in the Quarrel of the late King of Glorious Memory; where this great merit lies, I cannot well underſtand: for theſe reaſons; firſt, they were his ſubjects, and ſo they were in duty bound to fight for him; ſecondly, they were Perſecuted by the Long Parliament, and that good King (upon pretence that he ſo much coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenanced them) was Perſecuted likewiſe for their ſakes, and ſo they were con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrained to ſtand by him, and for him, for their own preſervation; and there is one of His Subjects of that Religion that ſtipulated, and they drive a bargain with the late King, before he would engage him. The Author would have us belive, that Dinner-Bells were miſtaken for Maſs-Bells: Do the Papiſts Dine at Six, Seven, or Eight of the Clock in the Morning? All their Inſolencies, the Author would perſwade us to attribute to the height of their zeal againſt Conſtables, or other Perſons in Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority, formed againſt the King; when it is very well known, that during the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bellion, when the late Rebels, <hi>Cromwel, Bradſhaw,</hi> and the reſt, were in humane ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pearance, confirmed in their Throne, none were better uſed, that went under the name of Cavaliers, than Papiſts; and now, ſince the happy Reſtauration of our Gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious Sovereign, many of theſe endeavor to ſtrike in with the Phanaticks; deſiring them to joyn with them, and they will take an order with the Epiſcopal Party: theſe are the men that ſo much boaſt themſelves of their Loyalty.</p>
                        <p>As to the Burning of <hi>London,</hi> God reward them according to their demerit, that were the Authors of that Diſmal and Execrable Fire; this is moſt certain, that the Papiſts rejoyce much in thoſe ſad Flames; and it is a common ſaying amongſt them, That the burning of that City is a happineſs to the Kingdom, and hath cured it of the Rickets.</p>
                        <p>It is now time to draw to a concluſion, though perhaps ſome things in the Pamph<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>let
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:206445:17"/>(being ſtuffed with many ridiculous paſſages) and little pertinent to the pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe, I have, for brevities ſake, omitted to ſpeak to.</p>
                        <p>For a Farewel, I will only add this to the Author; that if the Proteſtant aſſertors of his Majeſties Right, had been as few as thoſe he has ſet down in red Letters of his Party, he ſhould have been imitated by me; but our Numbers are ſo vaſt, that many large Folio's would not contain them.</p>
                     </div>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
            </q>
            <p>But inſtead of the Apologiſts Bloody Liſt, take here an extract of ſome things out of the Hiſtory of <hi>Henry</hi> the Fourth of <hi>France,</hi> written by <hi>Hardovin de Perefix,</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Rodez,</hi> formerly Tutor to this <hi>French</hi> King <hi>Lewis;</hi> concerning the League in <hi>France,</hi> called by its Abettors, <hi>The Sacred <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nion;</hi> ſupported by Popes, and more eſpecially by <hi>Sextus Quintus,</hi> and <hi>Gregory</hi> the Fourteenth, and entred into (by perſwaſion of the <hi>Roman</hi> Divines) by the Rebellious <hi>Roman</hi> Catholick Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects of the two <hi>Henries,</hi> the third and the fourth; to oppoſe which, they were moſt chiefly aſſiſted by their Proteſtant Subjects, who were always moſt ready to help them in time of extremity, and ſtill proved their beſt and moſt Loyal Subjects.</p>
            <p>On all hands little notice is taken of <hi>Henry</hi> the Fourth his Right to the Crown of <hi>France,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Fol. 61. The Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor writes thus concerning the ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſion of <hi>H<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>n.</hi> 4. to the Crown of <hi>France.</hi> 1584. year of our Lord.</note> becauſe he was removed above the ſeventh degree of Blood from <hi>Henry</hi> the Third of <hi>France,</hi> beyond which there is no kindred as to private Succeſſion; beſides he was not of that Religion which was ever profeſſed by the <hi>French</hi> Kings, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver ſince King <hi>Clovis,</hi> and conſequently was incapable of wear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Crown, and bearing the Title of <hi>Moſt Chriſtian, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Some <hi>French</hi> Divines, for the promotion of the League,<note place="margin">Fol 66. a Popiſh Principle, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning Kings, A. Dom. 15<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>4.</note> and ſince approved by Pope <hi>Sextus Quintus,</hi> did maintain, That the Prince ought to be depoſed, that did not to his duty; that power is only of God which is well regulated; otherwiſe, when it is ill ordered, it is not Authority, but Thievery; the words in the Original are thus,— <hi>Qui'il ny à que la puiſſance bien ordonne qui Soit de Dieu, autrement quand elle est dere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>glee te n'eſt pas autorite, mais Brigandage, &amp; qu'il eſt auſſi abſurde de dire que celuy la Soit Roy, qui ne Soait pas gouverner, &amp; qui eſt deſpouruen d'entendement, comme de croire qu'un avengle puiſſe ſervir de guide, on qu'une Statue imobile puiſse faire mounoir des hom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mes vivans.—</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Then came News from <hi>Rome,</hi> that the Pope <hi>Sextus Quintus,</hi> who ſucceeded <hi>Gregory</hi> the Thirteenth, had approved the League, and,<note place="margin">Fol 68. Auno Dom. 1585.</note> over and above, had thundered out his Bulls of Excommunicati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on againſt the King of <hi>Navar,</hi> and the Prince of <hi>Conde,</hi> declaring them Hereticks, Relaps, Cheiſs, Fautors, and Protectors of Hereſie, and as ſuch fallen into the C<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>n<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures, and Penalties imported by the Laws and Canons; deprived them, and their Heirs, of all Lands and Dignities; and uncapable to ſucceed to any principality whatſoever; and more eſpecially to the Kingdom of <hi>France;</hi> abſolving their Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects from their Oath of Allegiance, with a command not to obey them.</p>
            <p>When <hi>Henry</hi> the Fourth (then King of <hi>Navar</hi>) heard what the Pope had done againſt him,<note place="margin">Fol. 71. Anno Dom. 1585.</note> he ſent preſently to King <hi>Henry</hi> the Third, to complain thereof, and let him know that it concerned
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:206445:18"/>him, more than himſelf; That he might well think, if the Pope took upon him thus, to determine of the Succeſſion to his Kingdom, and declare a Prince of the Blood uncapable of the Crown, he might afterwards proceed farther, and unthrone him, as here-tofore Pope <hi>Zachary</hi> had degraded <hi>Childerick</hi> the 3d.</p>
            <p>The Pope gives to the Duke of <hi>Joyenſe</hi> all the King of <hi>Navarr</hi>'s Territories.<note place="margin">Fol. 82. Anno Dom. 1687.</note>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Henry</hi> the Third is Excommunicated by Pope <hi>Sextus Quin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Fol. 100. Anno Dom. 1589.</note>
            </p>
            <p>The Leaguers would have the Duke of <hi>Mayenne</hi> to take upon him the Title of King of <hi>France,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Fol: 101. Anno Dom. 1589.</note> which he refuſes, but accepts another Title which they give him, to be Lievtenant General of the State and Crown of <hi>France,</hi> as if the Throne were empty. The Leaguers break the Kings great Seal, and make a new one; on the one ſide thereof, were the Arms of Eſcutchion of <hi>France;</hi> and on the other, and empty Throne, with this Inſcription about the new Seal [Charles <hi>Duke of</hi> Mayenne, <hi>Lievtenant of the State and Crown of</hi> France.]</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Henry</hi> the Third being kill'd by a <hi>Roman</hi> Prieſt, called <hi>Jaques Clement,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Fol. 112. Anno Dom. 1589.</note> a <hi>Jacobin,</hi> thoſe that did not oppoſe him, becauſe he was a <hi>Roman</hi> Catholick, did believe themſelves obliged to joyn with the Leaguers againſt the King of <hi>Navar,</hi> now King of <hi>France,</hi> by the Death of the foreſaid King <hi>Henry</hi> the Third, becauſe he was an <hi>Hugonot;</hi> for the Papiſts of that Kingdom do hold, that none can be King of <hi>France</hi> that is not a <hi>Roman</hi> Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick.</p>
            <p>The reproaches of the <hi>Pariſians,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Fol. 139. Anno Dom. 1591.</note> the inſtant deſire of the Legate (whom the Pope had ſent to countenance and uphold the concerns of the League) and the <hi>Spaniſh</hi> Cabal, oblig'd the Duke of <hi>May<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>enne</hi> to give Battel to King <hi>Henry</hi> 4th. of <hi>France.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Paris</hi> being beſieged by the <hi>French</hi> King, the Popes Legate for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>got, and omitted nothing,<note place="margin">Fol. 152. Anno Dom. 1590.</note> that might encourage the <hi>Pariſians</hi> to hold out; he conſulted the Faculty of Divinity, and obtained from that Society, ſuch Reſolves againſt the <hi>Bearnois</hi> (for ſo was called by the Leaguers <hi>Henry</hi> the Fourth) as he thought good; the Legate cauſed ſeveral Proceſſions, and all Officers took an Oath of Fidelity to the Holy Union; for ſo was the League called by its Abetttors.</p>
            <p>In the mean time <hi>Sextus</hi> the Fifth dies, leaving in the Treaſury of the Church; five Millions of Gold;<note place="margin">Fol. 182. Anno Dom. 1591.</note> to him ſucceeded <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>rban</hi> the Seventh, who dyed within 13 days; and to <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>rban</hi> ſucceeded <hi>Gre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gory</hi> the Fourteenth, who with very much zeal ſupported the League.</p>
            <p>The King of <hi>Spain</hi> was ſeconded by Pope <hi>Gregory</hi> the Fourteenth in his Aſſiſtances to the Leaguers,<note place="margin">Fol. 185. Anno Dom. 1591.</note> who was much more eager and earneſt, than the ſaid King, for them; for notwithſtanding all the Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters and entreaties from the Lord of <hi>Luxemburg</hi> (afterwards Duke of <hi>Piney</hi>) and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Princes and Lords, who continued with <hi>Henry</hi> the Fourth; and being deaf likewiſe to the Submiſſions and Remoſtrances made to him by the Marquiſs of <hi>Piſani</hi> (deputed by the Pope) he very hotly embraced the Inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſts of the League;<note place="margin">Theſe Sixteen, were the chief A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bettors of the League in <hi>Paris</hi>
               </note> he kept correſpondence with the Sixteen, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiving Letters from them, and writing to them again: Moreover,
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:206445:18"/>the Pope did prodigally laviſh the Treaſure left him by <hi>Sextus Quintus,</hi> to raiſe an Army of 12000 men, which he ſent to ſuccor and aſſiſt the League; the Command whereof he gave to Count <hi>Hercules Sfondrati</hi> his Nephew, (whom he made Duke of <hi>Montmortion</hi> at that inſtant, for the greater luſtre;) and this Army was ſecond<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by a Minatory, or Bull of Excommunication, againſt all Prelates that ſhould aſſiſt King <hi>Henry,</hi> and ſent this Bull by <hi>Marcellin Londriane</hi> his Nuntio, with a great quantity of Money to be diſtributed amongſt the Sixteen, and other Chiefs of the Faction, in the Principle Cities of <hi>France.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Parliament at <hi>Tours</hi> cauſed the Bull to be torn by the hands of the Common-hangman, and ordined Seizure of the Popes Nuntio: On the other ſide, the Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament at <hi>Paris</hi> repealed this Decree, Ordaining that the Pope and his Nuntio muſt be obeyed.</p>
            <p>King <hi>Henry</hi> receives Succors out of <hi>England,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Fol. 191. Anno Dom. 1592.</note> and from the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtants of <hi>Germany,</hi> and then Beſieges the City of <hi>Roan.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>King <hi>Henry</hi> turns Papiſt,<note place="margin">Fol. 211.212.213. An. Dom. 1593.</note> and is abſolved by the Arch-biſhop of <hi>Bourges,</hi> in the Abbey-Church of St. <hi>Denis:</hi> Againſt the ſaid Biſhop the Pope is very angry, for abſolving the King; and till he obtain it of the Pope, his Rebellious <hi>Roman</hi> Catholick Subjects refuſe to obey him; nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther would the Pope be perſwaded to grant the King his Abſolution, till his Majeſty had, upon the matter, totally ſuppreſſed the League.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Jean Caſtel,</hi> a young Student educated by the <hi>Jeſuites,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Fol. 223.224. A. Dom. 1599.</note> attempts to kill the King, but by good fortune, only wounded him in the Face; whereby the Society of <hi>Jeſuites</hi> are baniſhed out of <hi>France;</hi> and their Scholar is executed, for this wicked and lewd Attempt.</p>
            <p>King <hi>Henry</hi> the Fourth, is kill'd by <hi>Ravilliac,</hi> who never expreſſed any kind of ſorrow or Repentance for ſo wicked a Fact; being perſwaded he had done the Pope, and the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> a very acceptable Service; becauſe he thought that King was Marching into <hi>Germany,</hi> to overthrow the <hi>Roman</hi> Catholick Faith there.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:206445:19"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
